<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apocalyptical mysteries, touching the two witnesses, the seven vials, and the two kingdoms, to wit, of Christ, and of Antichrist, expounded. Wherein is contained some things necessary for the saints in this present generation to know ... By H.K. a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299133</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299133</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2807:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Apocalyptical mysteries, touching the two witnesses, the seven vials, and the two kingdoms, to wit, of Christ, and of Antichrist, expounded. Wherein is contained some things necessary for the saints in this present generation to know ... By H.K. a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 35, [1], 45, [1], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In three parts. Each part has special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Eschatology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:1"/>
                  <p>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES, Touching the <hi>Two</hi> WITNESSES, the <hi>Seven</hi> VIALS, and the <hi>Two</hi> KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOMS, <hi>to wit,</hi> of CHRIST, and of ANTICHRIST, EXPOUNDED.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is contained ſome things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Saints in this preſent GENERATION to know. And therein is alſo ſhewed, what the IS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAEL of God ought to do in this DAY.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> H. K. <hi>a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa. 26.20, 21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Come my people, enter thou into thy Chamber, and ſhut thy doors about thee; hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be overpaſt. For behold, the Lord cometh out of his place to puniſh the Inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity: The earth alſo ſhall diſcloſe her blood, and ſhall no more cover her ſtain.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London.</hi> Printed in Year, 1667.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:2"/>
                  <head>To all the Saints, that in every place call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Name of the LORD Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THey that would ſerve God in their <hi>Generation,</hi> according to his <hi>Will,</hi> ought to inquire dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently into the particular Truths of the <hi>Age</hi> they live in, which are <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded</hi> in his Holy WORD. The <hi>dayes</hi> wherein we live, being not onely the latter <hi>Times</hi> of the firſt Apoſtaſie, propheſied of by the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3.</hi> but the laſt dayes of thoſe peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Times mentioned by him, <hi>2 Tim. 3.1, 5.</hi> I conceive, that the laſt part of God's revealed Will, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> hath in it thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:179884:3"/>Truths, which more <hi>peculiarly</hi> belonged unto this Age wherein we live; which conſideration hath made me willing (as my occaſions and daily Imployment would permit) to be ſearching them out. And though I cannot ſay that I have in all things found the <hi>Truth,</hi> which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and above others, may be called the <hi>Truth</hi> of this <hi>Age,</hi> and of our <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration;</hi> Yet being incouraged by that <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> promiſed <hi>Rev. 1.3.</hi> I have crouded my ſelf into the number of thoſe that run <hi>to</hi> and <hi>fro</hi> to find it: And have by ſearching the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> found three <hi>Myſteries,</hi> wherein are ſome things that ſeem to relate unto this <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> wherein we live, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the two <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> of the ſeven <hi>Vials,</hi> and of the two <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> to wit, of Chriſt, and of Antichriſt. Which I have made the Subject of this little <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> in the reading whereof, I doubt not but you will find ſome Truths that are <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179884:3"/>for the Saints in this <hi>Age</hi> and preſent <hi>Generation</hi> to know, and alſo ſome duties which the ISRAEL of God ought to do in this DAY and <hi>Age</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we live.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dear Brethren,</hi> How ever others may cenſure me for preſumption, in offering my Opinion in thoſe things, that are in their judgment too high and deep Myſteries for me to meddle with; Yet you that are Saints, know how to bear thoſe infirmities and weakneſſes of your <hi>unworthy</hi> Brother, which <hi>happily</hi> you may diſcern in reading this <hi>Treatiſe;</hi> And notwithſtanding them all, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any glimmerings of light that is held forth to you in the Expoſition of theſe Propheſies; that ſo you and I, who have our Fathers Name written in our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, may go hand in hand <hi>(like loving Brethren)</hi> about our Fathers WORK, following our LORD the <hi>Lamb</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goes. The Diviſions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and Separations that to this
<pb facs="tcp:179884:4"/>Day remains among the Profeſſors of this Age, cauſeth me to think, That God hath not done all his WORK upon Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> There are ſome ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings yet behind, which will purge away that droſs, by the Spirit of Judgment, and by the Spirit of Burning: And this is one Reaſon among others, which makes me think, the two Witneſſes are not yet ſlain; And though many of Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants have ſuffered for the Teſtimony which they held, yet there remains a Remnant of their fellow Servants and Brethren which ſhall be killed as they were, and this muſt be fulfilled: For, as there was ſuch a Diſpenſation under the ſeven Seals, <hi>Rev. 6.9, 10, 11.</hi> before God would avenge their Blood; ſo there ſhall be ſuch a Diſpenſation under the ſeven Trumpets, before the ſeven Vials of Gods laſt Plagues be poured out, <hi>Rev. 11.7, 18.</hi> And when I conſider the <hi>Congregations</hi> of Saints, &amp; <hi>Churches</hi> of ſeveral perſwaſions, <hi>in this Age,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179884:4"/>how unlike they are to the Churches of God recorded in the Scripture, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto Miniſtry, Gifts, and Diſcipline or Government, beſides what is amiſs in the Worſhip of God; It makes me think, That the Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony in Heaven is not opened, out of which Temple <hi>John</hi> ſaw the ſeven Angels come, who had the ſeven golden Vials of the ſeven laſt Plagues of God, <hi>Rev. 15.1, 5, 6.</hi> And if ſo, then the ſeven Vials are not yet any of them poured out upon <hi>Myſtical Babylon;</hi> for thoſe ſeven golden Vials were given them after they were come out of the Temple, <hi>Rev. 15.5, 6, 7.</hi> and they had not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to pour out any of the ſeven Vials till after that, <hi>Rev. 16.1, 2, 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The late <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of ſome, who have fallen in with the corrupt ſelf-ſeeking intereſts of this ſinful and ſuperſtitious <hi>Generation;</hi> and the <hi>Zeal</hi> of others, who have ſeparated themſelves from their Brethren, judging them to be
<pb facs="tcp:179884:5"/>defiled with the ſins of the <hi>times,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dare not have and hold Communion with them, though they hope they are Saints, and the dear Chilaren of God, hath given me occaſion to publiſh my Teſtimony at this time for the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> wherein I have ſaid ſome things that may, <hi>by the bleſſing of God,</hi> tend unto the recovery of ſome <hi>backſliders,</hi> and to the rectiſying of the Judgments of my zealous Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and to the reducing of thoſe Saints unto repentance, who have been defiled with any ſins of this Age or Generation, not of wilfulneſs, but through weakneſs, and that either for want of light, or through the strength of ſome temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; who being overtaken with a fault, ſhould be reſtored in the ſpirit of meekneſs, <hi>Gal. 6.1, 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which bleſſings of God ſhall pleaſe to effect, by theſe my poor endeavours, and labour of love, as I know he will not forget it, ſo I pray for you, and beg your prayers for me, that neither I nor you may forget to give him the glory.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>This done, I remain your Brother in the beſt Bonds, <hi>H. K.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179884:5"/>
                  <head>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES, The Firſt Part, Touching the <hi>two</hi> WITNESSES.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev. 11.3, 14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And I will give power unto my two Witneſſes, and they ſhall propheſie a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore days cloathed in ſack-cloth. The ſecond Wo is paſt, and behold, the third Wo cometh quickly.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>IT is not my intent to expound <hi>every verſe,</hi> and interpret <hi>each particular</hi> thing therein contained, but to offer my <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> briefly touching ſome things which I conceive are of more <hi>general</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179884:6"/>and may be of more <hi>ſpecial</hi> uſe unto the Saints at this DAY.</p>
                  <p>The Particulars which I have thought moſt neceſſary to treat of touching this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, are principally theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Who are the two Witneſſes, and what is their Teſtimony?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>What is their Power, and the time of their Propheſying?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Who the Beaſt is, and how he kills them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>What is the ſtreet of the great City, in which their dead bodies lie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>VVhat Time is to be underſtood by the three dayes and an half?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>How they ſhall be raiſed again, and what are the Effects thereof?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As touching the firſt, <hi>viz. VVho are the two VVitneſſes, and what is their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The two <hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> verſ. 3. are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>Metaphorically</hi> by two Olive Trees, and two Candleſticks, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are the two Olive Trees, and the two Candleſticks ſtanding before the God of the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By which Deſcription it appears, that the two Witneſſes are not any two <hi>individual</hi> Perſons, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> nor is thereby meant any two particular Teſtimonies, <hi>as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179884:6"/>the Old and New Teſtament,</hi> or two diſtinct Callings, <hi>as Magiſtracy and Miniſtry;</hi> for none of theſe Interpretations will agree with this Deſcription of the two Witneſſes, as will plainly appear in the Expoſition of this <hi>fourth verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the <hi>two Olive Trees</hi> are myſtically ſignified the Lords Miniſters and Prophets, who are here called <hi>Sons of Oyl,</hi> which is an <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> and a <hi>Metaphorical</hi> Expreſſion borrowed from <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.11, 14. <hi>Theſe are the two Anointed Ones that ſtand by the LORD of the whole Earth.</hi> Such were the Prieſts and Prophets of the LORD, who were Anointed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.41. &amp; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.16. Yea, and all the Saints who are a Royal Prieſthood, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. have an <hi>Unction</hi> from the Holy One, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20, 27. but eſpecially the Lord's Miniſters and Prophets, who being <hi>anointed</hi> with the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> above their fellow-Brethren the <hi>Saints,</hi> do empty the golden <hi>Oyl</hi> out of themſelves into the <hi>ſeven</hi> Lamps of the golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks.</p>
                  <p>By the <hi>two Candleſticks,</hi> are figured forth the viſible true conſtituted <hi>Churches</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as plainly appears by his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.20. <hi>And the ſeven Candleſticks are the ſeven Churches.</hi> As
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179884:7"/>
                     <hi>one</hi> Candleſtick in the Prophets Viſion <hi>usy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically</hi> ſignified that <hi>National</hi> Church of God, which was but One, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.2. So <hi>two</hi> Candleſticks in the Apoſtles Viſion <hi>Metaphorically</hi> repreſenteth thoſe <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational</hi> Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, which are many.</p>
                  <p>Nor is my diſtinguiſhing between the Lords Miniſters, and Prophets, and his Churches unwarrantable; for they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in other Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.4.22, 23. <hi>The Apoſtles and Elders with the whole Church, Acts</hi> 20.17, 18. alſo <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>And God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Teſtimony</hi> which theſe <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> bear, whilſt they propheſie in Sackcloath, is not that general <hi>Teſtimony</hi> which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Churches of God <hi>in all Ages of the Goſpel</hi> have born againſt Sin, Satan, and the World of ungodly men; though that may turn unto them for a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> but it is a <hi>Generation Confeſſion</hi> of thoſe Truths which do <hi>properly</hi> belong unto that <hi>Age</hi> wherein they live, and unto which they are called, as was <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, John</hi> 1.19, 20, 23. the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8. &amp; 4.18, 19. 20.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179884:7"/>
                     <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 18.5. and 23.11. <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12. And the Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. in their DAY.</p>
                  <p>So that this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is that <hi>confeſſion</hi> of Truth, which the Churches of God, and the Miniſters and Prophets of the Lord have made, and the Witneſſe, which they have born in their <hi>own</hi> Generation for Chriſt, his Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Churches, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Worſhip, and Government, or Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and againſt Antichriſt, or the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> his Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Churches, Ordinances, Worſhip, and Government, or Diſcipline, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereby the Saints in this preſent Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, may underſtand three things, which are neceſſary for them to know, and to do, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Churches, Miniſters, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the LORD are to bear their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, not onely againſt the Power, Throne, and great Authority which the Dragon (<hi>who is the Devil,</hi> Chap. 20.2.) gave unto the Beaſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.2. but alſo againſt all the Kings of the Earth, who have received their power at the ſame time with the Beaſt, and give their power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.12, 13. <hi>to wit,</hi> thoſe ten Kings of the fourth Monarchy,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179884:8"/>who received a <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Power one hour (<hi>or at the ſame time</hi>) with the Beaſt, and have given their <hi>moral</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and <hi>natural</hi> ſtrength unto the Beaſt; and <hi>principally</hi> againſt the <hi>Politick</hi> and <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick</hi> power of the <hi>eighth</hi> Beaſt, who is alſo one of the <hi>ſeven</hi> Kings who goeth into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Churches, Miniſters, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the LORD, are to bear their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, not only againſt the moſt groſs <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters</hi> of the great VVHORE, <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> and her <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> but alſo againſt the ſuperſtitious <hi>Abominations</hi> of all other Harlots, <hi>to wit,</hi> falſe Churches, and falſe VVorſhippers, who are her Daughters, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.5. Yea, though they be <hi>well-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured</hi> Harlots, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.4. called the <hi>Cities</hi> of the Nations, (<hi>that is to ſay, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Churches</hi>) who ſhall fall in the utter deſtruction of <hi>great Babylon,</hi> when ſhe comes in remembrance before God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Churches, Miniſters, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the LORD, are to beat their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony unto the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt here on Earth, not onely as he is King of <hi>Saints, Chap.</hi> 15.3. and King of <hi>Zion, Pſal.</hi> 149.1, 2. but alſo as he is King of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179884:8"/>
                     <hi>Nations, Jer.</hi> 10.7. For this <hi>confeſſion</hi> of the Kingdom of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt, is <hi>properly</hi> the Truth of this preſent <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Generation;</hi> the <hi>glad tydings</hi> whereof, is to be preached in all the <hi>WORLD</hi> for a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> unto all Nations, and then ſhall the END of the <hi>WORLD</hi> come, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.14. And I may ſay in the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. <hi>This is written for our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, upon whom the Ends of the VVorld are come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As touching the ſecond, <hi>viz. VVhat is the Power of theſe two VVitneſſes, and the time of their Propheſying?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Power,</hi> which the Lord hath given unto his two <hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> is not a <hi>Magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> Authority or Dominion, but a <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Power, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Power of the <hi>VVORD,</hi> not the Power of the <hi>Sword;</hi> which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon, why I cannot be of their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who ſay, That theſe two VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, are the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Prophetical</hi> Power, is declared by ſeveral Acts, <hi>(ſuch as were done by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the LORD of old) verſ.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>to wit.</hi> firſt Power over Fire, as <hi>Eliah</hi> had, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.10. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Behold I will make my words in thy mouth Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:179884:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Power over VVaters, both the VVaters that are above the Firmament, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. <hi>Theſe have power to ſhut Heaven, that it rain not in the dayes of their Propheſie.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>prophetical Power Elijah</hi> or <hi>Elias</hi> had, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.1. <hi>There ſhall be no dew nor rain, but according to my VVord;</hi> which the Prophet effected by <hi>earneſt</hi> prayer, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. And alſo over the VVaters which are under the Firmament, to turn them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Blood, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. As <hi>Moſes</hi> the LORD'S Prophet did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.19, 20, 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly, Power to ſmite the Earth with all Plagues;</hi> which Plagues are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Metaphorically</hi> of Spiritual Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: For although the <hi>Prophetical</hi> Power of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> and other Prophets, brought <hi>material</hi> Plagues, and <hi>temporal</hi> Judgments upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, &amp; upon the Inhabitants of the world, yet the Plagues and Judgments here <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> deſcribed are, <hi>if not onely, yet princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally</hi> of a Spiritual kind, ſuch as the Lord: Prophets of old alſo had <hi>Power</hi> to do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.13, 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Time</hi> of their Propheſying is 1260, dayes, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. The ſame <hi>number</hi> of 1260. the <hi>WOMAN</hi> (that is to ſay, the <hi>Church</hi> of God) is fed in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> chap. 12.6.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179884:9"/>
                     <hi>to wit,</hi> by thoſe Miniſters and Prophets, who are the Witneſſes of Chriſt, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Which 1260. dayes, counting 30. dayes for a month, make <hi>forty two</hi> months, which is the time that the holy City (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of God) ſhall be troden under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot by the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> by the Papiſts and Popiſh Idolaters, who for their Spiritual Idolatry in the Worſhip of God, are called <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as the great <hi>City,</hi> Myſtical Babylon, <hi>Spiritually</hi> is called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> verſ. 8. And the number of forty two months is the time that was given unto the Beaſt (<hi>viz.</hi> Antichriſt, that Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Antichriſtian <hi>Politick</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Power and Dominion) to continue, and to prevail, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.5, 7. Hereby it doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that as the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> who tread the holy <hi>City</hi> underfoot, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.2. and the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that doth make war with the <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of the LORD, and overcome them, and kill them, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.5, 7. &amp; 11.7. are one and the ſame time of forty two months; ſo the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>WOMAN,</hi> who is fed in the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs</hi> chap. 12.6. and the time of the two <hi>Witneſſes</hi> propheſying in <hi>Sackcloath,</hi> chap. 11.3. are one and the ſame <hi>time</hi> of 1260.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179884:10"/>dayes. And it hereby alſo appears that all theſe <hi>four</hi> are contemporary, <hi>all beginning and ending together;</hi> and beſides that which is noted touching theſe <hi>four,</hi> and their <hi>time</hi> in the Scripture of Truth, both the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Hiſtory, and the late <hi>Expoſitors</hi> of this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> do give a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> unto the ſame, <hi>affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that when the Beaſt began to exerciſe his <hi>Tyrannical</hi> Power, and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the Saints, then the Holy <hi>City</hi> began to be trodden under foot, then the <hi>Woman</hi> fled into the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and then the two <hi>Witneſſes</hi> began to Propheſie in <hi>Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the <hi>Beasts</hi> Antichriſtian <hi>Politick</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiastick</hi> Power <hi>coercively</hi> was (<hi>ſay they</hi>) about the Year of our Lord, 407, 409, 410. or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.
<q>As may be ſeen in <hi>Symſons</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Church, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Socrat. Hist. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Helvicus in Concil. Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinatenſ. cap.</hi> 7. The Councel of <hi>Toled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> in <hi>Spain, Anno Dom.</hi> 400. as ſaith <hi>Helvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. Magdeb. Cent. 5. cap.</hi> 10.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is not my work at preſent to determine either the <hi>beginning</hi> or <hi>ending</hi> of this <hi>time,</hi> but onely to give the Interpretation of theſe 1260, dayes, which contain the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179884:10"/>time of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> propheſying in <hi>Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The 1260. dayes are not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>litterally</hi> of ſo many <hi>natural</hi> dayes, for that is but three years and an half, which is intended by the <hi>three dayes and an half,</hi> verſ. 9. when the dead bodies of the ſlain Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes lie unburied, called a Time, and Times, and half a Time, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.14. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.21, 25.</p>
                  <p>But we muſt underſtand thoſe 1260. dayes <hi>prophetically,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>each day for a year,</hi> according unto thoſe Scriptures, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.5, 6.</p>
                  <p>So that, <hi>The whole time of the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes propheſying in Sackcloath, is</hi> 1260. <hi>years.</hi> So long the <hi>holy City</hi> is to be trodden under foot; ſo long the <hi>Woman</hi> is to be in the <hi>VVilderneſs;</hi> and ſo long the <hi>Beast's</hi> Power is to continue; for the times of all theſe four do begin and end together, and are but one time, <hi>to wit,</hi> 1260. years.</p>
                  <p>As touching the third Particular, viz. <hi>Who the Beast is, and how he kills the VVitneſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The great Monarchs and Monarchies of this WORLD, have been figured forth by <hi>wild Beasts;</hi> God ſhewed his Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> the <hi>four</hi> Kingdoms by a Viſion of <hi>four</hi> Beaſts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>The first like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179884:11"/>a Lyon, the ſecond like to a Bear, the third like a Leopard;</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> Beaſt, <hi>to wit, the Roman Kingdom,</hi> was ſo dreadful, that he had no <hi>Name,</hi> ſo monſtrous, that he had no <hi>reſemblance</hi> unto any one Beaſt, but is deſcribed by ſuch things as doth manifeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him to be a <hi>Monster,</hi> to wit, <hi>partly</hi> a Man, by his two <hi>Iron</hi> Legs, by his Feet, and te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Toes, <hi>part of Iron, and part of Clay, Dan.</hi> 2.33. which is expounded of the fourth Kingdom, <hi>verſ.</hi> 40, 41, 42, 43. and <hi>part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> a Beaſt, by his great <hi>Iron</hi> teeth, by his te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Horns, and a little Horn <hi>that came up among them, Dan.</hi> 7.7, 8. which is alſo expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the fourth Monarchy, <hi>verſe</hi> 24, 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Roman Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>And our LORD Jeſus Chriſt gave the like Deſcription of the fourth Monarchy, or Roman Kingdom, unto his Servant <hi>John,</hi> under the ſimilitude of a Beaſt, namely, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> great red Dragon, Revel.</hi> 12.3. Which Beaſt was terrible and monſtrous, (<hi>as that which</hi> Daniel <hi>ſaw</hi>) all ſpotted like a Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, his feet like a Bear, and his mouth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the mouth of a Lyon, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.3. with <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> Heads and <hi>ten</hi> Horns, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.3. <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending out of the bottomleſs Pit, and goeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Perdition,</hi> v. 8. And this is the Beaſt which ſhall kill the <hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> chap. 11.7.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:179884:11"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Beast</hi> in this Propheſie is ſometimes mentioned alone, without any diſtinction, and then we are thereby to underſtand the whole complex Body of the Roman Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Politick &amp; Eccleſiaſtick State and Government, as <hi>chap.</hi> 14.9, 11. And in other places of this Book the Beaſt is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned with ſome other, <hi>as if he were two,</hi> as the Beaſt that roſe out of the Sea, and the Beaſt that roſe out of the Earth, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.1, 11. Beaſt and Woman, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.3. the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, <hi>chap.</hi> 19.20. And thereby we are to underſtand a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wo-fold Power mixed and exerciſed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is to ſay, by the Beaſt is meant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Political, and by the Woman, the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Power of the Roman Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent.</p>
                  <p>So then by the Beaſt, <hi>that kills the VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> verſ. 7. we are to underſtand the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oman-Antichriſtian-Politick-and-Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſtick-State and Government exerciſed <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ercively</hi> over mens Conſciences in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lace or Caſe whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Beast, that ſhall kill the two VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> is more diſtinctly (<hi>though more My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ically</hi>) deſcribed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8, 11. by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ee particular things. <hi>First,</hi> By his paſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſent, and future State; The Beaſt that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179884:12"/>WAS, and IS NOT, and yet IS. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> By his twofold number; even he is the EIGHT, and is of the SEVEN. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By his RISE and RUINE; He ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs PIT, and go into PERDITION,</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Beaſt</hi> that WAS, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.11. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> Monarchy, or <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, and the <hi>Political</hi> Government thereof WAS a Kingdom which God ſet up, and a Power which God ordained, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.40.7.7, 23. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 7.</p>
                  <p>The Beaſt that WAS, and IS NOT, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> is to ſay,</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> Monarchy, or <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom in its <hi>mixt</hi> State of <hi>Politick</hi>-and, <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Government, <hi>coercively</hi> exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed over the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of men in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Place</hi> or <hi>Caſe</hi> whatſoever, IS NOT God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ORDINANCE; For the <hi>Dragon</hi> (which is the <hi>Devil,</hi> Chap. 20.2.) gave this <hi>Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his Power, and his Seat, and great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.2.</p>
                  <p>The Beaſt that WAS, and IS NOT, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yet is, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.8. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> Monarchy, or <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a Power ordained of God, with reſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its <hi>meer</hi> Political Government, but I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> NOT God's Ordinance in its <hi>mixt</hi> State <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Politick-and-Eccleſiaſtick Power and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179884:12"/>Yet IS a <hi>Power,</hi> and hath a <hi>Throne,</hi> chap. 13.2. Yea, and exerciſeth great <hi>Authority</hi> over the Bodies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men <hi>coercively;</hi> and cauſeth both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and bond, to receive his <hi>Mark</hi> in their right hand, or in their foreheads; and cauſeth that as many as would not worſhip the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſhould be killed, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that WAS and IS NOT, even he IS the <hi>EIGHTH,</hi> chap. 17.11. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the eighth <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and IS of the <hi>SEVEN,</hi> which <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Iniquity, that we may with more clearneſs underſtand; the Angel told <hi>John,</hi> that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that carrieth the <hi>Woman,</hi> had <hi>ſeven</hi> Heads, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.7. which he ſaith are <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> Kings, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> ſeven kinds of <hi>political</hi> Governours, and <hi>forms</hi> of Government in the fourth Kingdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>FIVE are fallen,</hi> or were paſt and gone before <hi>John</hi>'s time, namely, 1. Kings, 2. Conſuls, 3. Decim-vers, 4. Tribunes, and 5. Dictators: <hi>ONE</hi> is, <hi>to wit, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors,</hi> who being the <hi>ſixth</hi> head of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ruſed and exerciſed their <hi>Dominion</hi> over the whoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom in the dayes of our Saviour and his Apoſtles; the <hi>OTHER</hi> is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179884:13"/>not yet come, <hi>to wit,</hi> the <hi>ſeventh</hi> Head of the <hi>Beaſt, that is to ſay,</hi> the ſeventh King, or kind of Government was not yet in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when <hi>John</hi> writ this <hi>book</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation; which <hi>ſeventh</hi> Head is Popes, for they <hi>ſucceeded</hi> the <hi>Emperors</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Government of the Roman <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire (as all Hiſtorians teſtifie)</hi> and have ruled and reigned as Kings.</p>
                  <p>And this Beaſt is the <hi>EIGHTH,</hi> viz. the <hi>eighth</hi> Head, with reſpect of his <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastical</hi> Power, mixed with his Political-Authority; And is of the <hi>SEVEN, that is to ſay,</hi> he is <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>ſeven, to wit,</hi> the ſeventh Head or King, with reſpect of his <hi>Political-Power</hi>-and-Authority. And this mixed <hi>Politick</hi>-and-<hi>Eccleſiastick</hi> Power, is ſignifyed by his <hi>two</hi> Horns, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.11, 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs PIT,</hi> chap. 17.8. <hi>&amp;c</hi> chap. 11.7. <hi>The Beast that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs Pit,</hi> viz. the Helliſh Apoſtacy of the latter times, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. which is contemporary with the opening o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the bottomleſs Pit, <hi>chap.</hi> 9.1. So is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> falling away (<hi>or Apostacy</hi>) with the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the man of Sin, this ſon of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. this King is the Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179884:13"/>of the bottomleſs Pit, <hi>chapter</hi> 9.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And go into Perdition,</hi> chap. 17.8. <hi>and</hi> verſe 11. <hi>goeth into PERDITION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The man of Sin, <hi>Antichrist,</hi> is called the <hi>SON</hi> of <hi>PERDITION,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. and it is <hi>twice</hi> affirmed, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.8, 11. that he goeth and ſhall go into <hi>PERDITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON,</hi> becauſe the thing is certain: And the meaning is, that the <hi>BEAST</hi> of the <hi>eighth</hi> Head, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the Roman-Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-Pollitick-and-Eccleſiaſtick-Power, Dominion, and Government, together with the Antichriſtian-<hi>POWERS,</hi> Potentates, Kings, and Governours, who exerciſe that <hi>Antichristian</hi>-power and dominion <hi>coercive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> over the Bodies, Eſtates, and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, ſhall be utterly deſtroyed; which <hi>utter</hi> Deſtruction and <hi>PERDITION</hi> will be fully effected and compleated by pouring out of the <hi>ſeven</hi> VIALS of the laſt Plagues, <hi>for in them is filled up the wrath of God,</hi> chap. 15.1. &amp; 16.1, 10, 19. &amp; 18.2, 8. &amp; 19.19, 20, 21. &amp; 14.9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>And the third Angel followed them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a loud Voice, If any man ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the BEAST and his IMAGE, and receive his MARK in his Forehead, or in his Hand; the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the WRATH of God, which is poured out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179884:14"/>MIXT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE, into the C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it be enquired how the BEAST doth kill the Witneſſes? <hi>I anſwer,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The BEAST ſhall 1. make WAR againſt them; 2. He ſhall OVERCOME them; and 3. He ſhall KILL them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Beast</hi> cannot <hi>overcome</hi> them as <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> (for ſo they Overcome him, and the Dragon alſo, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.11. <hi>And they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him by the Blood of the Lamb, and by the Word of their Teſtimony</hi>) but as <hi>Warriours,</hi> chap. 13.7. <hi>And it was given to him to make War with the Saints, and to overcome them.</hi> This WAR is a more open and viſible <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> between the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> &amp; the BEAST, then <hi>formerly,</hi> though the <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> had oppoſed the <hi>Beast,</hi> and born their <hi>Testimony</hi> againſt his mixt Antichriſtian <hi>Power,</hi> and Idolatrous <hi>Worſhip,</hi> from the <hi>beginning</hi> of the 1260. <hi>dayes</hi> of their <hi>Sackcloath</hi>-conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they did more privately; And though the <hi>Beast</hi> had perſecuted the <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> for the <hi>Testimony</hi> which they bare againſt him, from the <hi>beginning</hi> of the 42. <hi>months</hi> of his <hi>Power;</hi> Yet now at <hi>last,</hi> and toward the <hi>end</hi> of their 1260. <hi>dayes,</hi> the two Witneſſes bear a <hi>more manifest Testimony,</hi> and make a <hi>more open and Viſible Oppoſition</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:179884:14"/>y againſt both the <hi>Tyrannical</hi> Power, and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> Worſhip of the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Beaſt</hi> now at laſt, and toward the <hi>end</hi> of his 42. <hi>months,</hi> begins to rage, and maketh a greater and <hi>more cruel Oppoſition,</hi> both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> of the LORD, who are the <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> and all the Saints; by exerciſing his Power more <hi>tyrannically</hi> againſt them; which is the WAR here mentioned, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. as that was, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.7. In the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>fifth,</hi> in <hi>Germany, France, Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. and in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>this</hi> WAR the <hi>Beaſt</hi> overcomes the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> verſ. 7. as in <hi>that</hi> he overcame the Saints, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.7. Some of the Witneſſes are overcome by <hi>fear,</hi> and others by <hi>flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> ſome by his <hi>alurements</hi> and preferments, others by his <hi>threats</hi> and confinements are overcome for a time; ſo far as to ceaſe from <hi>bearing</hi> their Teſtimony againſt him ſo <hi>openly</hi> and <hi>vigorouſly</hi> as they did before; In which reſpect the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is here ſaid to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>But this will not appeaſe the <hi>rage,</hi> and great <hi>wrath</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> for he perceives that the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> which the Witneſſes bear in their more private <hi>Retirement,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, <hi>(as they are called)</hi> or Meetings,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179884:15"/>will like a Moth waſte, &amp; ſecretly conſume his Power and Dominion, and at laſt (if let alone and ſuffered to enjoy any liberty to meet together to <hi>worſhip</hi>) his Power and Dominion will be utterly deſtroyed, as is Propheſied, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26. And therefore the <hi>Beaſt</hi> will take Councel together with his chief Prieſts to KILL the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of the LORD, (as the high Prieſt, the chief Prieſts and Elders did to put our <hi>Saviour</hi> to death, <hi>John</hi> 11.47, to 53.) <hi>And KILL them,</hi> verſ. 7. The <hi>killing</hi> of the <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> doth not ſignifie a <hi>Corporal</hi> death only, nor principally, for ſuch a <hi>killing</hi> doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with this Propheſie; but it is rather a <hi>Metaphorical</hi> Expreſſion, which ſignifies a <hi>two-fold</hi> Death, partly Civil, whereby the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſhall be deprived of their <hi>civil</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of their Religion; their <hi>Eſtates</hi> confiſcated, their <hi>Perſons</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, Impriſoned, Baniſhed; and <hi>ſome</hi> of their <hi>Lives,</hi> or <hi>all</hi> their <hi>livelyhood</hi> taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the tyrannical Power of the Beaſt; and <hi>partly,</hi> yea principally Spiritual, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſhall be deprived of that <hi>Zeal, Vigor,</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> which with all boldneſs they had <hi>formerly</hi> manifeſted, in bearing their <hi>Teſtimouy</hi> openly for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Kingdom, his Church, his Worſhip,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179884:15"/>and his Government; againſt the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Beaſt,</hi> his Kingdom, Church, Worſhip, and Government.</p>
                  <p>The darkneſs and blackneſs of the DAY of the Witneſſes <hi>death,</hi> will <hi>principally</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in their being deprived of that <hi>Spirit of Life</hi> that ſometimes they had received from God, and had formerly exerciſed in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Teſtimony: which Spirit of Life the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> loſe by cooling in their <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> affections unto Chriſt, and by their ſinning againſt the LORD; for <hi>uſually</hi> when Miniſters or Members of Churches fall from their firſt Love, they fall in with the Apoſtacy of the time; and ſo loſe that life and courage which they formerly had, and manifeſted with great boldneſſe for <hi>Chriſt</hi> againſt Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Spiritual</hi> kind of death is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable unto their Reſurrection, that is effected by that Spirit of Life from God, which verſ. 11. <hi>after three dayes and an half</hi> ſhall enter into them. Now ſuch as is the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> ſuch is their <hi>death:</hi> But their <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is <hi>Spiritual,</hi> (for verſ. 11. <hi>the Spirit of Life from God entred into them</hi>) therefore their death is Spiritual, viz, <hi>A depravation of that Spirit of Life,</hi> that is to ſay, the loſs of that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179884:16"/>boldneſs, zeal, vigor, and life, which they formerly had, and manifeſted in their <hi>Testimony</hi> for <hi>Christ</hi> againſt the <hi>Beast.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This kind of <hi>death</hi> is alſo moſt agreeable unto the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> lying dead after they were <hi>killed,</hi> in reſpect both of the place, which is <hi>Spiritually</hi> called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> ver. 8. and of the time when they lay unburied, which is <hi>Prophetically</hi> ſaid to be three dayes and an half, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>Touching the fourth Particular, viz. <hi>What is the Street of the great City in which their dead Bodies lie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> unto this Particular is <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly</hi> given in the 8, &amp; 9. verſes of this Chapter, <hi>And their dead Bodies ſhall lie in the street of the great City,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The great City is <hi>that</hi> mentioned, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth, to wit,</hi> the WOMAN that ſits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Scarlet-coloured BEAST, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.3. which is the great WHORE, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.1. whoſe <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>Myſtery BABYLON,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of HARLOTS, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.5. <hi>viz.</hi> the whole <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Kingdom of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> all <hi>Myſtical</hi> Babylon.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Street</hi> of the <hi>great City</hi> is ſome <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> Street, <hi>(as a Market-Street)</hi> or ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179884:16"/>eminent Street, <hi>(as Cheap-ſide)</hi> or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Street or place <hi>(as Smithfield)</hi> within or without the <hi>great City,</hi> under the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Government thereof.</p>
                  <p>By this <hi>Street</hi> we are to underſtand ſome <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>minent Part</hi> of Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Beaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome of the ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms which appertain unto the Dominion of the Beaſt, and not his whole Kingdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the whole City: It is not ſaid in the <hi>Streets</hi> of the great <hi>City,</hi> but in the <hi>Street,</hi> to wit, the moſt eminent Kingdom for the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, even that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> have moſt <hi>eminently</hi> born their Teſtimony againſt Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>The place being ſpoken of by way of <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency,</hi> muſt be underſtood either in relation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> or in reſpect unto the Beaſt that kills them, or to both: Now take ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, or both together, and it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies not the whole <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> nor the whole Kingdom of <hi>Babylon,</hi> but a <hi>part</hi> thereof. Not the whole Kingdom of <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pon the riſing and aſcending of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, there is but a <hi>part</hi> of the Kingdom of Babylon falls, <hi>And the tenth part of the City fell,</hi> verſ. 13. which is that part here meant by <hi>this</hi> Street.</p>
                  <p>Nor all the VVitneſſes of Chriſt in all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179884:17"/>the WORLD, no nor in all the Kingdoms of <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe there are ſome Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes remain alive when theſe <hi>two</hi> are kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, who ſhall call upon them to come up to them, when the Spirit of Life from the Lord doth again enter into them, and cauſe them to ſtand upon their feet, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>And they heard a great Voice from Heaven ſaying unto them, Come up hither.</hi> Which Voice from Heaven, is the call of thoſe Angels, who have the ſeven laſt Plagues and come out of the Temple of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Teſtimony in Heaven when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is opened, to come up to Mount <hi>Zion</hi> to them, where they and other Saints ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the Lamb, and to ſee the Judgement of the great WHORE, which will appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by comparing, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.12, 19.14.1, 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 15.1, 2, 5, 6.17.1. <hi>And the Temple o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God was opened in Heaven, and there were voyces,</hi> chap. 11.19. <hi>And the ſeven An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels came out of the Temple — in Heaven</hi> chap. 16.6. <hi>And one of the ſeven Angels which had the ſeven Vials, ſaid, Come up hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I will ſhew thee the judgment of the great Whore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As touching the fifth Particular, <hi>viz. What time is to be underſtood by the three days and an half,</hi> verſ. 9.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:179884:17"/>
                  <p>The knowledge of the <hi>time</hi> when the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> ſhall be killed and riſe again, is very deſirable unto the Saints in this GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION; many godly and learned Men have laboured <hi>ſtudiouſly</hi> in ſearching out this <hi>time,</hi> and have communicated their underſtanding about this Matter; whoſe labours have been profitable unto the Lords people, and unto me alſo; who having read their Opinions about the <hi>ending</hi> time of the Witneſſes <hi>Sackcloath</hi>-condition, and of the <hi>troubles</hi> of the Lords People, I have been much comforted by ſeveral precious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations which they have made touching this matter: But not being fully ſatisfied with their Determination of the <hi>period</hi> of that <hi>ending</hi> time, I have alſo addicted my ſelf to ſearch the <hi>holy</hi> Scriptures touching ſuch <hi>Prophetical</hi> Numbers as ſeem to contain the <hi>ending</hi> time; And I ſhall take liberty to give my Opinion alſo, and the grounds thereof, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The three dayes and an half, are three years and an half; <hi>each day for a year,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prophetical Account of <hi>Myſtical</hi> dayes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The three dayes and an half, are thoſe three years and an half which do <hi>immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:179884:18"/>ſucceed the <hi>killing</hi> or death of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes;</hi> for after they are killed, their dead Bodies are ſeen three dayes and an half, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.9. and they do immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed their Reſurrection; for after three dayes and an half, the Spirit of Life from God doth enter into the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and they ſtand upon their feet, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.11. So then, <hi>The three years and an half are the time of the interval between the Death and the Reſurrection of the two Witneſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The three dayes <hi>(or years)</hi> and an half, is the <hi>ending-time</hi> of the Witneſſes 1260. dayes, <hi>(or years)</hi> and of the Beaſts 42. months (<hi>or</hi> 1260. <hi>years.</hi>) For the <hi>clear</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of this third Particular, let i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be conſidered;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the <hi>time</hi> when the <hi>Beaſt</hi> kills the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> is towards the end of the 1260. dayes or years of their Propheſying, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.7. <hi>When they are about to finiſh their Teſtimony;</hi> and therefore the Witneſſes are killed before the time of their 1260<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dayes or years be ended, <hi>to wit,</hi> three dayes <hi>or years</hi> and an half before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>killing</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>rejoycing</hi> over their <hi>dead bodies,</hi> are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>laſt</hi> Acts of the Beaſt's <hi>Tyrannical</hi> Power, and of the Whores <hi>Triumphing</hi> Joy; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179884:18"/>therefore muſt be near the <hi>ending</hi>-time of the Beaſt's 42. months, and alſo of the 42. months, wherein the Gentiles <hi>(who are the Idolatrous worſhippers of the Beaſt)</hi> tread the <hi>holy City (that is, the Church of God)</hi> under their feet.</p>
                  <p>That the killing of the Witneſſes is the <hi>laſt</hi> Act of the Beaſt's <hi>tyrannical</hi>-Power, <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears plainly;</hi> for as ſoon as the Witneſſes riſe, <hi>Babylon</hi> begins to fall, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.11, 13. <hi>And they ſtood upon their feet; and the ſame hour — the tenth part of the City fell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the rejoycing over their dead Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies is the <hi>laſt</hi> Act of the Whores <hi>triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>-Joy, appears plainly; for as ſoon as her Joy and Rejoycing is over, the day and hour of her Judgement came, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.7, 8, 10. <hi>For ſhe ſaith in her heart, I ſit as a Queen, and am no Widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow; therefore ſhall her Plagues come in one day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The things that the Saints in this GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERATION ought to know touching the time of the Witneſſes lying dead; Are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the <hi>time</hi> of the END, or the <hi>ending-time</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> propheſying in Sackcloth; of the Beaſt's <hi>tyrannical</hi> POW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER; of the <hi>holy City,</hi> her being troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot of the Gentiles, and of the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:179884:19"/>being in her <hi>Wilderneſs</hi>-condition, is near at hand; for the finiſhing Teſtimony is begun, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Goſpel of the Kingdom of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt, which is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fore-runner of the ending-time of this WORLD, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. <hi>And when they were about to finiſh this Teſtimony;</hi> That is, when they began to preach the Goſpel <hi>(or glad tydings)</hi> of the Kingdom; the Beaſt killed them, which is the laſt <hi>Act</hi> of his <hi>tyrannical</hi> POWER.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That although the <hi>ending-time</hi> be near, yet the <hi>period</hi> thereof will not be certainly known until the laſt three years and an half be begun, and well night expired, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4, 9. and <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. <hi>The Viſion is yet for an appointed time, at the END it ſhall ſpeak, and not lie; though it tarry, wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That when the <hi>ending-time</hi> is come and begun, before it be expired, there ſhall ſuch <hi>remarkable</hi> and <hi>wonderful</hi> things come to paſs (as are foretold in the Scriptures) whereby the wiſe ſhall underſtand, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know that it is the time of the END, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then will be ſuch tribulation, and ſuch a time of trouble as never was before, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.21, 22.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:179884:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Then will be ſuch an Apoſtacy among Profeſſors, Miniſters, Prophets, and Churches, as never was before, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. — 5. and 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Then will begin a very glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reformation in the Worſhip of God, by the Spirit of Life from God, which Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life entring into the ſlain <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> will ſet them upon their feet, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> will cauſe them again to ſtand up for Chriſt and his Kingdom, and againſt Antichriſt and his Kingdom: And then will the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God (<hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the Church and Worſhip of God) be opened in Heaven, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.19. <hi>Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the times of the reſtitution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the Mouth of all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oly Prophets ſince the WORLD began,</hi> Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.21.</p>
                  <p>Touching the laſt Particular, viz. <hi>How be Witneſſes ſhall be raiſed again, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re the effects thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Anſwer unto this Particular, is My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ically held forth in the 11, 12, 13, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. <hi>verſes</hi> of this <hi>Chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the <hi>time; After three dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d an half,</hi> verſ. 11. by which we are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>derſtand three years and an half, <hi>(as have before proved)</hi> that is to ſay, at or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179884:20"/>before the end of that time; for as it was ſaid of our LOKD and Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> After three days he ſhould riſe again, which he did on the third day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is likewiſe ſaid of his <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> after three dayes and an half, the Spirit of Life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet, according to what was foretold by one of the Lords Prophets, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>After two dayes he will revive us, in the thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> day he will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The means of the Witneſſes Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is <hi>the Spirit of Life</hi> from the Lord which entred into them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. viz. that Spirit Life, Power, Courage, Zeal, and Boldne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> which the two Witneſſes <hi>formerly</hi> had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God, and had exerciſed in bearin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their Teſtimony for the Kingdom of Chriſt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and againſt the Kingdom of Antichriſt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but had loſt by falling from their <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> love, and by falling in with the <hi>leſt</hi> Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; which Spirit of Life from God is again given unto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they ſtood upon their feet,</hi> verſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that is to ſay, The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were <hi>raiſed,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vived, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſtrengthened by the Spirit of Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from God; for as the loſs and departure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Spirit of Life and courage to bear the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179884:20"/>Teſtimony with boldneſs, was their death; ſo the Spirit of Life from God entring into them, and renewing their Courage, revive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Zeal, and increaſing their Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in bearing their Teſtimony, is their Reſurrection, and that which cauſeth them to ſtand upon their feet: which effect of the Spirit of Life from God, was typed out by the dry Bones of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Ezek.</hi> 37.5, 10, 14. <hi>O my People, — I will put my Spirit in you, and ye ſhall live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The LORD knows his Servants, his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are not able either to do much, or to ſay much for Chriſt and his Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor againſt Antichriſt and his Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs they be ſpirited thereunto; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when God had any eminent work or ſervice to do, he did not onely raiſe up In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to do it, but ſpirited them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Thus the Spirit of the LORD came upon <hi>Othniel,</hi> Judg. 3.9, 10. and upon <hi>Gideon,</hi> Judg. 6.34. and upon <hi>Jephthah,</hi> Judg. 11.29. and upon <hi>Sampſon,</hi> Judg. 14.6, 19. and 15.14. and upon <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 16.13. And ſo it will do upon the Lords <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> Rev. 11.11. <hi>And great fear came upon them</hi> (Enemies) <hi>that ſaw them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>effect</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or ſtanding upon their feet, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179884:21"/>concerned <hi>themſelves,</hi> verſ. 12. or their <hi>Enemies,</hi> verſ. 13.</p>
                  <p>Verſe 12. <hi>And they heard a great Voice from Heaven ſaying unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Witneſſes being raiſed and ſpirited for the WORK of the LORD, are now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereunto, which call is by <hi>a great Voice from Heaven;</hi> that is out of the Temple of God opened in Heaven, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.19. <hi>to wit,</hi> the Church of God on Earth, whoſe Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Glory is deſcribed, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.1. <hi>by a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man cloathed with the Sun,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This Voice, is the Voice of the <hi>Remnan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of the <hi>Womans</hi> Seed, who kept the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſts <hi>Goſpel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,</hi> Acts 1.2.) and have the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Jeſus, (<hi>viz.</hi> a Spirit of Propheſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>chap.</hi> 19.10.) even then, and all that time of the three years and an half, when the Witneſſes are killed, and their dead Bodies lie in the Street of the great City.</p>
                  <p>Which <hi>Remnant</hi> of the <hi>Womans</hi> Seed, do call upon the raiſed Witneſſes, ſaying unto them, <hi>Come up hither,</hi> verſ. 12. that is to ſay, <hi>Come</hi> and joyn with us, and worſhip God with us; <hi>Come</hi> and help us to carry on the Work of the LORD, his Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to pull down the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179884:21"/>Beaſt, which call or invitation of the Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the Witneſſes did ſtraightway anſwer as followeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they aſcended up to Heaven in a Cloud,</hi> werſ. 12. This ſignifies a <hi>glorious</hi> change in the ſtate of the <hi>VVitneſſes,</hi> attending their Reſurrection, which they now attended by their <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> called a Cloud, in which reſpect thoſe eminent Believers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Chapter,</hi> are called <hi>a Cloud of VVitneſſes,</hi> Heb. 12.11. And the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> ſwift aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, or going up unto thoſe that called them, is fitly reſembled unto a bright Cloud, as the Converſion of the Gentiles, and their coming into the Jews after their glorious Converſion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 8. <hi>VVho are theſe that flee as a Cloud,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the ſame hour was there a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> Verſ. 13. By this <hi>Earth-quake</hi> we are to underſtand great Commotions, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturnings, and downfals in the Kingdoms of Antichriſt, as <hi>chap.</hi> 6.12. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.7. which great Change is ſaid to happen the <hi>ſame hour</hi> with the Witneſſes <hi>Aſcention,</hi> that is to ſay, at the ſame time when the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> riſe, the Papiſts fall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the tenth part of the City fell,</hi> Verſe 13. By the City, here is meant the whole
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179884:22"/>Roman Antichriſtian Kingdom of the Beaſt as <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. and <hi>chap.</hi> 17.18. And by the <hi>tenth part</hi> of the City, we are to underſtand one of the ten Kingdoms of <hi>Myſtical</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, for the <hi>whole</hi> City conſiſting of ten Kingdoms, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.3. &amp; 13.1. and 17.12. the <hi>tenth part</hi> of the City muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſome ONE of the ten Kingdoms, <hi>to wit,</hi> that Kingdom where the <hi>VVitneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> lay ſlain, called the STREET of the great <hi>City,</hi> verſ. 8. And the <hi>Retaliation</hi> which follows, ſeemeth to favour this Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>And in the Earth-quake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand,</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>viz.</hi> ſeven thouſand men of Name; which fall of ſo many eminent Perſons of the Antichriſtian Party, will become a means of Converſion unto many others of that Party, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>And the Remnant were afrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Verſe 14. <hi>The ſecond VVOE is paſt, and behold the third VVOE cometh quickly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the <hi>ſecond</hi> WOE we are to underſtand all the Troubles, Plagues, and Judgements of the ſixth Trumpet, recorded from <hi>chap.</hi> 9.13. unto <hi>chap.</hi> 11.14. which are now paſt and ended. <hi>And the third VVOE cometh quickly, to wit,</hi> upon the ſounding of the <hi>ſeventh</hi> Trumpet, which is the <hi>third</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:179884:22"/>WOE-<hi>trumpet</hi> which is to be ſounded by the ſeventh Angel, <hi>chap.</hi> 8.13. which <hi>ſeventh</hi> Trumpet brings in the Diſpenſation of the <hi>ſeven</hi> Vials of the <hi>laſt</hi> Plagues of God upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is fitly called the third <hi>(or laſt)</hi> WOE.</p>
                  <p>Touching which <hi>third</hi> WOE, or <hi>Vials</hi> of the laſt Plagues of God upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> I have ſomething to offer in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Part of this little <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which I judge meet for the Saints in this <hi>Generation</hi> to know; And therefore I ſhall pray that God will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Scriptures unto you, <hi>(that ſhall read it)</hi> and open your underſtanding, that you may know the Truth, and what you ought to do in this <hi>day</hi> of your <hi>Generation.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:23"/>
                  <p>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES.</p>
                  <p>The Second Part, Touching the <hi>Seven</hi> VIALS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. Chapter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:24"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179884:24"/>
                  <head>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES. The Second Part, Touching the <hi>Seven</hi> VIALS.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Chapter</hi> containeth the Angels <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> to execute the wrath of God upon the Beaſt, and their <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> thereof gradually, by pouring out one <hi>Vial</hi> after another, until all the ſeven <hi>Vials</hi> of the ſeven <hi>laſt</hi> Plagues be poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Babylon,</hi> unto whom is given the <hi>Cup</hi> of the Wine of the fierceneſs of the wrath of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. of which <hi>Cup</hi> every one that worſhippeth the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> and receiveth his Mark in his Forehead, or in his hand, ſhall drink, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179884:25"/>
                  <p>The Angels <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is in the <hi>firſt verſe</hi> of this Chapter, <hi>And I heard a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Voice out of the Temple, ſaying, Go your wayes, and pour out the Vials of the wrath of God upon the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this <hi>Commiſſion</hi> obſerve Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the <hi>execution</hi> of the wrath of God upon <hi>Babylon;</hi> wherein you have, <hi>firſt,</hi> The Divine Authority of it, A <hi>great Voice out of the Temple; Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom the Command was given, <hi>Saying to the ſeven Angels, Go now. Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>work</hi> which they were commanded to do, Pour out the Vials of the wrath of God upon the Earth.</p>
                  <p>This great Voice was the Voice of the LORD, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.6. A <hi>Voice from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Voice of the LORD, that rendereth recompence to his Enemies.</hi> It is called a <hi>grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Voice; not onely to ſhew us that it is the Lord's Voice, but his Voice out of <hi>Zion,</hi> which is his <hi>Temple,</hi> as was propheſied <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. <hi>The LORD alſo ſhall roar o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of</hi> Zion, <hi>and utter his Voice from</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and the Heavens and the Earth ſhall ſhake</hi> Yea, to declare that the great <hi>day</hi> of the LORD is near, it is near, and haſtned greatly, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.14, 15. which diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the day of wrath, the Prophet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179884:25"/>
                     <hi>The Voice of the Day of the LORD,</hi> Zeph. 1.14, 15. And ſuch is that Voice which is uttered out of the <hi>Temple</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from the <hi>Throne,</hi> ſaying, It is done, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>of this Chapter;</hi> upon the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the <hi>ſeventh</hi> Vial.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Temple</hi> in this firſt verſe, is called, <hi>The Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Heaven,</hi> chap. 15.5. and <hi>the Temple of God opened in Heaven,</hi> chap. 11.19. And in the 17. verſe of this Chapter, <hi>the Temple of Heaven.</hi> Not that we are to underſtand it to be in Heaven, in reſpect of place, for <hi>John</hi> ſaw no ſuch Temple in the holy and Heavenly City, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.22. But by the Temple of Heaven, or in Heaven, is meant the Heavenly State of the Church of God on Earth, reſtored to its Apoſtalical inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and Primitive purity, called, <hi>the Temple of the Living God,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. It is called the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> to note, that the Church of God on Earth at this <hi>time</hi> of the pouring out of the ſeven <hi>Vials,</hi> is not ſo <hi>glorious,</hi> nor ſo <hi>fixed,</hi> as the <hi>Temple</hi> was in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, but rather doth reſemble the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the LORD, which had been in the Wilderneſs, and was come into the promiſed Land; in which <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179884:26"/>the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the preſence of God, <hi>Num.</hi> 9.15, 16. where was alſo the Ark of his Covenant, and wherein was the Service of God performed, and all his holy Sacrifices offered, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.17, 37, 40. And ſo when this Temple of the Tabernacle was opened, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. <hi>There was ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in his Temple the Ark of his Covenant;</hi> and thoſe who had waſhed their <hi>Robes,</hi> and made them white in the blood of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> that <hi>did ſerve him day and night in his Temple,</hi> chap. 7.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>The ſeven <hi>Angels</hi> which had command to pour out the <hi>Vials</hi> of the wrath of God, are them <hi>ſame ſeven</hi> who had the ſeven laſt <hi>Plagues,</hi> chap. 15.1. the ſame ſeven <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> came out of the <hi>Temple,</hi> verſ. 6. and the ſame ſeven <hi>Angels</hi> had given unto them ſeven golden <hi>Vials</hi> full of the <hi>wrath</hi> of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seven</hi> is a Prophetical Number, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying both <hi>variety</hi> of Inſtruments, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Judgements of God in this Propheſie, as the ſeven <hi>Trumpets,</hi> chap. 8.1, 6, 3. <hi>Some</hi> denouncing, and <hi>others</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting theſe laſt Plagues.</p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Angels</hi> are cloathed with pure and white Linnen, and girded with golden Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179884:26"/>
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 15.6. Their Cloathing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares ſome of them to be the Prieſts of God, for ſo were the Prieſts of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cloathed, <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.4. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.18. And this was the Lords Inſtitution, <hi>Exod.</hi> 39.27, 28, 29. Their being gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with golden Girdles, ſhews that others of them are the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of the LORD, into whoſe hand God will commit the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.21, 22, 23. The Miniſters of the Churches are called Angels, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.20. <hi>The Angels of the ſeven Churches.</hi> And Kings alſo are compared unto Angels, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.7. <hi>As an Angel of God, ſo is my Lord the King.</hi> The whole Deſcription teſtifies theſe Angels to be Kings and Prieſts unto God, whom Chriſt hath made ſuch, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10. who was ſo cloathed and girded himſelf, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.13. <hi>And in the midſt of the ſeven Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leſticks, was one like unto the Son of Man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>loathed with a Garment down to the foot, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>irt about the Paps with a golden Girdle;</hi> A Deſcription of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rieſt and King in his Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> But how can the pouring out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Vials of the Plagues of Almighty God, full of his great wrath, be applyed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179884:27"/>unto the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who an to preach the moſt precious ſweet ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaving Truths of Jeſus Chriſt, eſpeciall conſidering that by theſe Vials and Plague<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are meant the real and external Judgment and Plagues which God will have execute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by thoſe Angels upon the <hi>Whore,</hi> as appears <hi>chap.</hi> 18.8. <hi>Therefore ſhall her Plagues co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in one day, Death, Famine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Miniſters of the Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may be ſaid to pour out the Vials of God great wrath, even his real and materi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Plagues, and moſt righteous Judgments up on the great City <hi>Babylon;</hi> as the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of old are ſaid to root out, and pull dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and to deſtroy, and to throw down, <hi>Jer.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 10, 16. and to take the <hi>Wine-Cup</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lords <hi>fury</hi> at his hand, and to make a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nations (<hi>to whom God ſends them</hi>) to drin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.15, 16, 17, — 28. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this they did by pronouncing thoſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt them, which the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> commanded them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.16. Even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Miniſters of the Goſpel pour out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Vials of the wrath of God, &amp; real Plague<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> by pronounci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe laſt Plagues of the wrath of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe <hi>Angels</hi> come out of the Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179884:27"/>
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 15.6. <hi>after it was opened.</hi> This doth declare them to be the raiſed <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for the Temple was not opened (<hi>in the Viſion unto</hi> John) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il the <hi>ſlain</hi> Witneſſes were riſen, and had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcended the Throne, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.7, 11, 15, 17, 19. So their coming out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le ſignifies their Saint-ſhip, and that theſe Angels are <hi>fellow Citizens with the Saints, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd of the Houſhold of God, built upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner Stone, in whom all the Building fitly framed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ogether, groweth unto an holy Temple in the Lord,</hi> Eph. 2.19, — 22.</p>
                  <p>And who are more fit to declare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>engeance of the Lord, <hi>even the vengeance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f his Temple,</hi> Jer. 50.28. then the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſters</hi> of God in <hi>Zion?</hi> Or who are more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eet to execute the Righteous Judgments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f God upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> then thoſe Magiſtrates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto whoſe hand the LORD will commit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Government of Chriſts Kingdom here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Earth, called, <hi>The People of the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the most High,</hi> Dan. 7.27. whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ORD of Hoſts will make his Battle Ax, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Weapons of War, and with whom he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill break in pieces the Nations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oy Kingdoms, and render unto <hi>Babylon</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:179884:28"/>all the evil that ſhe hath done in <hi>Zion, Jer.</hi> 51.20, 24.</p>
                  <p>Leſt it might be dubious how the Saint or true Worſhippers in the Churches, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Magiſtrates, ſhould execute th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fierceneſs of Gods wrath upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the Beaſt, conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſome of the Angels which came out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Temple,</hi> may be alſo the <hi>holy</hi> Angels of God who are ſaid to be about the <hi>Throne</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Temple, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.11. worſhipping God wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the four living Creatures, and twenty for Elders, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.11. and who are ſaid to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> company the Saints, that were cloathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with white <hi>Robes,</hi> and <hi>Palmes</hi> in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.9, 10, — 15. (<hi>an Emble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the victory they had gotten over the Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and his Image,</hi> chap. 15.2.) For the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Angels of God are preſent in the Aſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. 1 <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. And they are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forth to miniſter for them; and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may be ſaid alſo to come out of the Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (<hi>as well as the Saints</hi>) to execute th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> righteous Judgements of God upon <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> chap. 18.1, 2. And Chriſt alſo, <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> is the Angel of the Covenant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the <hi>Earth,</hi> here we are to underſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>earthly</hi> State of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as it is contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:179884:28"/>diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Heavenly</hi> State of <hi>Zion,</hi> which is the true Church of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1. <hi>I ſaw a Star fall from Heaven to the Earth;</hi> which was the viſible <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> from the <hi>Heavenly</hi> State of the True Church of God, for ſoundneſs of Doctrine, purity of Worſhip, and power of Diſcipline, to an <hi>earthly</hi> State of a falſe Church, with reſpect unto corrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſuperſtitious Worſhip, and <hi>tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Diſcipline, after the Inventions and precepts of Men.</p>
                  <p>And as the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. is a genetal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earm, which comprehended the Land, the Seas, the Firmament, with the Sun, Moon, and Stars; the Air, and all Men, Beaſts, Fowls of the Air, and every creeping thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat God created and made out of that Maſs or <hi>Chaos.</hi> So by the Earth <hi>here</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Earth, Sea, Sun, Seat, and all other things of the Beaſts deviſing, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioned in this Chapter; and alſo thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abiters of the Earth, which are the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of the three dreadful WOES menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned, <hi>chap.</hi> 8.13. whereof the third <hi>Woe</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontains the 7. <hi>Vials</hi> of the laſt Plagues of God to be poured forth upon thoſe Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers of the Earth, who are the worſhippers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd admirers of the Beaſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 13. 8. 17. 8. &amp; 14. 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179884:29"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Saints</hi> having gotten the <hi>victory</hi> over the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and over his <hi>Image,</hi> and over his <hi>Mark,</hi> and over the <hi>number</hi> of his <hi>Name;</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> in Heaven being opened; the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline of the <hi>Church</hi> of God in ſome meaſure <hi>reſtore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to their primitive <hi>Purity;</hi> the ſeven <hi>Angels,</hi> who have the ſeven laſt <hi>Plagues,</hi> being come out of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and having received ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven golden <hi>Vials</hi> full of the <hi>wrath</hi> of God, with commiſſion and expreſs command to execute the <hi>fierceneſs</hi> of the Wrath and Plagues of God, poured out their <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> upon the earthly State of the Beaſt, and Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> and upon all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that Earth, <hi>to wit,</hi> the worſhippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and admirers of the Beaſt; as hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before declared and proved in the Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>firſt verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the firſt</hi> (Angel) <hi>went and poure our his Vial upon the Earth.</hi> verſ. 2. of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Beaſts Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>The Earth <hi>in Scripture</hi> is often taken fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> an Earthly-State-Apoſtacy in any Natio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or Kingdom, upheld by men of corru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Minds, and earthly Intereſts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8 This Earthly-Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Apoſtacy is propheſied of, and foretold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:179884:29"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Apoſtle to be in the <hi>laſt dayes,</hi> 2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1, — 5. and is moſt likely to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the laſt Plagues which are to be poured out of the ſeven <hi>Vials</hi> upon the Earth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. This <hi>Earth</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Kingdom, is that <hi>Earth,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants <hi>rejoyced</hi> over the Witneſſes and Warriors of the LORD, when they were <hi>ſlain</hi> by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and their dead <hi>Bodies</hi> were not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be put in <hi>Graves,</hi> chap. 11.10. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom that third <hi>WOE</hi> is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>chap.</hi> 8.13. and upon whom this firſt <hi>Vial</hi> is to be poured out. As the dry Land is called the <hi>Earth,</hi> Gen. 1.10. ſo by the <hi>Earth</hi> in this <hi>ſecond verſe,</hi> we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſome thing in the Beaſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that bears a fit and full reſemblance unto the dry Land.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. For Foundations.</item>
                     <item>2. For all manner of Flood.</item>
                     <item>3. For fulneſs of Riches, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.5, 14.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And therefore by this <hi>Metaphorical</hi> Earth, we are to underſtand, the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Doctrines, and Principles of all falſe Religions, as the Doctrine of Juſtification by Works, the Doctrine of Popiſh Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, the Doctrine of Purgatory, Maſs, worſhipping of Images, Croſſes, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179884:30"/>Altars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Doctrine of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Inventions of men; the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Magiſtratical and Miniſterial Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>coercively</hi> to be exerciſed over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, in the Matters of God, his Worſhip and Government, both Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, and Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which like the dry Land, <hi>(called Earth) Firſt,</hi> Doth ſeem to ſtand ſo firm, that they ſhall not be removed for ever. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> Out of thoſe Earthly Doctrines is produced all manner of Food for them that make their belly their God, as the Abbots and Prieſts do. Alſo <hi>thirdly,</hi> Out of thoſe <hi>Earthly</hi> Doctrines is produced abundance of <hi>riches,</hi> all their Temples, Cathedrals, Abbies, Friaries, Nunneries, Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, have been founded and built upon this Earth, which they that are the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Earth, thought ſhould never be removed, chap. 18.7. <hi>For ſhe ſaith in ber heart, I ſit a Queen, and am no Widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow.</hi> Yea, the Popes themſelves, and their Cardinals, Arch-Biſhops, Prelates, Prieſts, and <hi>all the Clergy,</hi> (have been founded, fed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by theſe earthly Doctrines) who are the Inhabiters of this Earth, upon which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179884:30"/>this firſt <hi>Vial</hi> ſhall be poured out, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the third <hi>Woe</hi> is pronounced, <hi>chap.</hi> 8.13. and upon whom the ſad effects of this firſt <hi>Vial</hi> will inevitably fall, <hi>viz.</hi> a noyſom and grievous ſore which fell upon the men which had the <hi>Mark</hi> of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and upon them which <hi>worſhipped</hi> his Image; which bears ſome <hi>alluſion</hi> unto one of the noyſome and grievous <hi>Plagues</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod. 9.10, 11. This Sore being <hi>noyſome,</hi> cauſeth both Lovers and Friends unto <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to ſtand afar off for fear of her Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>chap.</hi> 18.10, 15, 17. And it being a <hi>grievous</hi> Sore, cauſeth much pain and torment unto the worſhippers of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> chap. 14.8, 9, 10, 11. [which are the properties of ſuch Sores, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.11. &amp; 77.2.]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond Angel poured out his Vial up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sea</hi> of the Beaſts Kingdom, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> upon the <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, Forms, Ordinances, Maſſes, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Will-worſhips, and all other <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Superſtitions, and Inventions of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> that great <hi>Whore,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of Harlots, (<hi>viz. both ill-favoured and well-favoured Harlots</hi>) the Catholick and National Churches of <hi>Rome, Spain, France,</hi> &amp;c. which Idolatrous Worſhip, (like the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179884:31"/>Sea, when it is troubled, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.20.) is full of mire and dirt. As the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the Waters is called <hi>Seas,</hi> Gen. 1.10. ſo the gathering together of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils, National Synods, Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Viſitations, Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are called Seas, as the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Popes Sea, the Cardinals Sea, <hi>Canterburies</hi> Sea, <hi>Yorks</hi> Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Sea of Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Kings of the Earth, the Merchants of the Earth, Maſters of Ships, and as many as Trade by Sea do trafick for the States and Souls of men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chap. 18.9, 11. The <hi>effects</hi> of this <hi>Vial</hi> is blood and death unto the Idolatrous and Superſtitious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers. Behold, the righteous <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of God, and his juſt <hi>Retaliation</hi> unto the Scarlet and Bloody <hi>Whore,</hi> and falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other Myſtical <hi>Seas</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Churches in any Nation, whoſe <hi>Sea,</hi> by the pouring out of this <hi>ſecond Vial,</hi> ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like the <hi>blood</hi> of a dead Man, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>living</hi> Soul died in this Sea.</p>
                  <p>And this Plague <hi>alſo</hi> may have ſome <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion</hi> unto that <hi>Plague</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> Exod. 7.20, 21. whoſe <hi>Waters</hi> was turned into <hi>blood,</hi> and the <hi>Fiſh</hi> that was therein died. So <hi>bloody</hi> and ſo <hi>deadly</hi> is the Idolatrous-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179884:31"/>of the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of all other Nations that worſhip the <hi>Beaſt</hi> or his <hi>Image,</hi> who ſhall utterly be deſtroyed, as appears, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third Angel poured out his Vial upon the Rivers and Fountains of Waters</hi> in the Beaſts Kingdom, verſ. 4.</p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Myſtical</hi> Rivers and Fountains of Waters, bear ſome Alluſion unto thoſe <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial</hi> Rivers and Fountains which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, run into the <hi>Sea,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.7. As the Fountains or <hi>Spring-heads</hi> run into the Rivers, and the Rivers run into the Sea; ſo the Emperors, Kings, Princes, and Nobles of the Roman Antichriſtian Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Eccleſiaſtick Government and Kingdom, give their power and ſtrength unto the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> chap. 17.12, 13. And to his Councels, Synods, Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is the River into which theſe Fountains run, and ſo into the Sea of <hi>Rome, Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> &amp;c. The great Monarchs of this World, and Kings of the Earth, are ſaid in Scripture to be the Head of their Rivers, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29.3, 4. &amp; 32.2, 6. <hi>I will alſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with thy blood the Land wherein thou ſwimeſt,</hi> &amp;c. Again, as the Fountains do ſignifie Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo by the <hi>Rivers</hi> into which their ſtreams do continually run and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179884:32"/>are filled, and influenced by them, is meant the Antichriſtian Hierarchy, Popiſh Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and all the falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> Teachers, and Prieſts, and upon all that are in <hi>holy Orders, (as they ſpeak)</hi> who preach the Doctrine of the Beaſt, and worſhip his <hi>Image;</hi> ſuch as theſe are called <hi>Wells,</hi> (though without any <hi>living and refreſhing</hi> Water) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 17. And they are here fitly reſembled unto <hi>Rivers</hi> of Waters in the Beaſts Kingdom. This Antichriſtian Monarchy, Hierarchy, Popiſh Clergy, Prieſts and Prelates, (like the Rivers and Fountains in and about a great City, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 18.27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.2.) though they ſpoil the Land, and waſte the City, and foul the Waters, [for as a Fountain caſteth out her filthy Waters, ſo do theſe corrupt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains caſt out their wickedneſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.7.] yet that great City, <hi>Myſtical Babylon,</hi> is made very great, (<hi>and like the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>of old,</hi> Ezek. 31.3, 4, 5.) her <hi>height</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and ſhe is <hi>enriched,</hi> becauſe of the multitude of theſe Waters and Fountains of hers, whoſe Nurſeries and Seminaries, like the deep, with her Rivers running round about their Plants, ſend out their little Rivers unto all the Trees of the field, and into the deep Sea.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179884:32"/>
                  <p>The <hi>effect</hi> of this <hi>Vial</hi> is their own blood, which God in his <hi>righteous</hi> Judgements gives thoſe Monarchs, Kings, Prelates, Prieſts, and all the Popiſh Church and Clergy-men to drink, as a juſt <hi>Retaliation</hi> of the blood of the faithful Saints, and Sackcloath <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> which this <hi>Scarlet Beaſt</hi> and <hi>bloody</hi> Whore of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſhed, by perſecuting and killing them, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. &amp; 11.7.17.4, 5, 6. &amp; 18.20, 24. For which Judgments the LORD is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all his Saints, and holy Angels in Heaven and on Earth, <hi>to be Righteous;</hi> and his Judgements alſo are acknowledged by them <hi>to be true and Righteous,</hi> verſe 5, 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fourth Angel poured out his Vial upon the Sun</hi> of the Beaſts Kingdom, verſ. 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> Upon the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c. with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Temporal and Political part of the Beaſt's Kingdom, and upon the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Popiſh Cardinals, and Arch-Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with reſpect to the Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical part of the Beaſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; thoſe Antichriſtian Emperors, Kings, Popes, and Prelates, (like the Sun in the Firmament of Heaven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18.) are moſt eminent and chief Lights, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179884:33"/>have the moſt eminent Grandeur, Rule and Dominion in the Firmament or Fabrick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Beaſt's Politick and Eccleſiaſtick Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Kingdom; and are fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled by the Sun, and other Lights <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Heaven, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>effect</hi> of this <hi>Vial,</hi> is the <hi>ſcorching of men with great heat,</hi> verſ. 9. By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> power that was given unto this <hi>Angel</hi> ſo t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. The men that are ſcorched with fire, and with great heat, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, 9. are thoſe men of the Beaſt's Kingdom, who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>who are tormented with Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and Brimſtone,</hi> which cauſeth them to <hi>blaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pheme</hi> the Name of God, who hath powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> over theſe Plagues; <hi>And they repented n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to give him glory,</hi> verſ. 9. The Fire an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Heat, are the <hi>burning Heat and devouring Fire</hi> of the fierceneſs of God's great wrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poured out of this <hi>Vial</hi> upon the Sun, which cauſeth thoſe dreadful Effects, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>And ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with Fire; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the fifth Angel poured out his Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> upon the Seat of the Beaſt,</hi> verſ. 10.</p>
                  <p>Who this fifth Angel is, the Expoſitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>firſt verſe</hi> gives us to underſtand <hi>viz.</hi> Some of thoſe Magiſtrates into whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:179884:33"/>hand God will commit the Government of the Kingdom of Chriſt, (<hi>as was proved before</hi>) And ſome of thoſe Miniſters of his Churches, who ſhall come out of the Temple, <hi>even</hi> ſuch of his Saints as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath redeemed and made <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> unto God, who ſhall reign on Earth, aſſiſted by Chriſt, <hi>the Angel of the Covenant,</hi> and his <hi>Heavenly</hi> Angels, to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute</hi> the righteous <hi>Judgments</hi> of God, (<hi>as was alſo proved before</hi>) by pouring out of the Vials of the wrath of God.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Vial</hi> is one of thoſe ſeven golden <hi>Vials</hi> which was given unto the ſeven An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which were full of the wrath of God, and contained the laſt Plagues, which are to be poured out upon Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> to her utter deſtruction, <hi>as hath been proved, before,</hi> and chap. 16. verſ. 19. and all them that worſhip the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> chap. 14.8, 9, 10, 11. Theſe <hi>Vials</hi> are called the <hi>Cup</hi> of Gods Indignation, and the <hi>Cup</hi> of the Wine of the fierceneſſe of his wrath.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>Object</hi> of the Wrath of God, even of the <hi>fierceneſs</hi> of his great Wrath, upon whom the LORD will pour out all his <hi>Plagues</hi> firſt and laſt, and <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſhall drink the <hi>Cup</hi> of his Indignation,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179884:34"/>
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 14.10. <hi>and the nineteenth verſe of this Chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beaſt</hi> in this <hi>Propheſie</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is ſometimes named without any diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then by <hi>Beaſt</hi> we are to underſtand the whole Complex Body of the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Politick and Eccleſiaſtick State of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, <hi>Church,</hi> and Government, as <hi>chap.</hi> 11.7, 13.18, 14.9, 11. and ſometimes the Beaſt is named with diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.11, 12. as if there were <hi>two</hi> Beaſts, both which is but <hi>one</hi> Beaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by his <hi>twofold,</hi> Power, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, <hi>to wit,</hi> Political and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, as doth appear, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. &amp; 4. So <hi>chap.</hi> 17.3. the Beaſt and the Woman, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the Political Government, and the Eccleſiaſtick State; likewiſe <hi>chap.</hi> 16.13. and 19.20. the Beaſt, and the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; alſo the Beaſt and his Image, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.14. By the <hi>Beaſt</hi> we are to underſtand the <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſtian Political State Power and Dominion. By the <hi>Woman,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is the <hi>Whore,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of the Beaſt, and the <hi>falſe</hi> Prophet, <hi>(in divers reſpects)</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are to underſtand the Roman Antichriſtian Eccleſiaſtick State, Church, Worſhip, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Government. The <hi>Reaſon</hi> of this <hi>diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is the <hi>two-fold</hi> Authority and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179884:34"/>which the <hi>Beaſt</hi> exerciſeth in the World, and in the Church; and therefore the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is ſaid to riſe from <hi>two</hi> places, <hi>to wit,</hi> out of the <hi>Sea,</hi> Chap. 13.1. and out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> verſ. 11. and to have <hi>two</hi> Horns like the <hi>Lamb,</hi> chap. 13.11. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> a two-fold Power, <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> both which was given unto the Beaſt by the Dragon, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.2. <hi>And the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon gave him his Power, and his Throne, and great Authority.</hi> Which Dragon is called the old Serpent, the Devil, and Satan, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.9. &amp; 20.2. <hi>And he laid hold on the Dragon, that old Serpent, which is the Devil, and Satan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the <hi>Beaſt</hi> then in this <hi>verſe,</hi> is meant the Roman Antichriſtian Politick and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick State, Kingdom, Rule, Power, Dominion, Worſhip, and Government, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wit,</hi> the whole <hi>Complex</hi> Body of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hriſt,</hi> who hath his Power, Throne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat Authority given unto him by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il, and doth by virtue thereof exerciſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth a Political and Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And this Roman Politick and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſiaſtick State, is that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth the Father and the Son, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. and that <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> and Son of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdition, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3, 4, 9, 10. <hi>Who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179884:35"/>and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped,</hi> even that Beaſt that aſcended out of the bottomleſs Pit, and goeth into Perdition, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.8, 11. As the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the Object of the wrath of God, ſo the <hi>Seat</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>Subject</hi> upon which this <hi>fifth Vial</hi> of his wrath is poured out.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the fifth Angel poured out his Vial upon the Seat of the Beaſt,</hi> verſ. 10.</p>
                  <p>By the <hi>Seat</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Place, <hi>even</hi> the <hi>principal</hi> place where the Beaſt doth exerciſe his Power and great Authority; which is <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo all other great Cities where the Beaſt hath his Reſidence, his Throne, his Courts, and exerciſeth his Grandeur and great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. The City of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Mountains on which the <hi>Woman, that is,</hi> Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſitteth, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.5, 9. And the <hi>Seat</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> being diſtinct from his Power and Authority, <hi>as it is,</hi> chap. 13.2. it muſt be interpreted of the place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Beaſt's <hi>Reſidence,</hi> where his <hi>Throne</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> placed, and his Power and great Authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is <hi>principally</hi> exerciſed.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>effects</hi> of this <hi>fifth Vial</hi> are four.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> A great <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the Beaſt's fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Greatneſs, Grandeur, and Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:179884:35"/>
                     <hi>And his Kingdom was full of darkneſs; that is to ſay,</hi> The Beaſts Kingdom and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion both in the Political and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part thereof was <hi>totally</hi> eclipſed, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and clouded.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> effect of this <hi>Vial</hi> will be the extremity of Rage that the worſhippers of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> will fall into; <hi>And they gnawed their Tongues for pain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>third</hi> effect of this <hi>Vial,</hi> will be their blaſphemy againſt God; <hi>And they blaſphemed God becauſe of their pain and ſores.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> effect will be, an impenitent frame of hardneſs of heart; <hi>And they repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not of their deeds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that although the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and ſome of his worſhippers live, after his Kingdom and Dominion, both Political and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal be deſtroyed, yet they repent not of their Idolatries, which cauſeth God to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in his Judgments, and to pour out the 6th and 7th Vials upon them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the ſixth Angel poured out his Vial up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the great River</hi> Euphrates, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Object</hi> of the <hi>wrath</hi> of God poured out of this <hi>Vial,</hi> is the River <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was a <hi>River</hi> that ran through <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia</hi> unto old <hi>Babylon,</hi> which by way of <hi>Eminency,</hi> above all other <hi>Rivers,</hi> is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179884:36"/>called <hi>the great River, the River</hi> Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.4. unto which this may bear ſome alluſion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what that <hi>natural</hi> River was to <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> Babylon, this <hi>Metaphorical</hi> River is to <hi>Myſtical</hi> Babylon. The <hi>principal</hi> benefits of a great River are two, <hi>viz.</hi> Revenue, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.3. <hi>The Harveſt of the River is her Revenue;</hi> and Strength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.7. <hi>The Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the River ſtrong and many,</hi> even <hi>the King of</hi> Aſſyria <hi>and all his glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> here we are to underſtand that which is the Harveſt of <hi>Babylons</hi> Revenue, and the Puiſſance of her ſtrength at this juncture of time, when the Throne of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> by the pouring out of the fifth Vial, was broken, and in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure deſtroyed. That the day of Gods great wrath will be upon the Merchandiſe of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> viz. her Merchandiſe of Gold and Silver, precious Stones and Pearls, Purple and Scarlet, Wine and Oyl, Corn and Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, Slaves and Souls of Men, is manifeſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 18.10, 11, 12, — 17. <hi>For in one hour ſo great Riches is come to nought.</hi> And by that Judgment of God upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> her great Revenue (<hi>which is one Stream of the great River</hi>) is dryed up.</p>
                  <p>But the ſtrength of <hi>Myſtical</hi> Babylon <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:179884:36"/>forth by this great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> (in this 12. verſe) is the great Turk, and his numerous and mighty People; who will be at this juncture of time aiding and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>Myſtical</hi> Babylon, againſt Chriſt and his <hi>Zion;</hi> for which Cauſe God will pour out this Vial of his wrath upon both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> and upon all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Multitudes, who are the Waters of this great River, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.15. And the Reaſon why I rather incline to this <hi>Opinion, (than the former)</hi> is, becauſe all Expoſitors do interpret <hi>the great River</hi> Euphrates, <hi>chap.</hi> 9.14. to be the Turks. Now conſidering that this <hi>great River</hi> is mentioned but in thoſe <hi>two</hi> places of this Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Under the ſixth Trumpet, <hi>chap.</hi> 9.14.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> Under the ſixth Vial, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.12.</p>
                  <p>I conceive it is moſt probable that one ſort or Nation of People is intended in both places, to wit, the <hi>Turks,</hi> who then did, and now do inhabit about that great River <hi>Euphrates;</hi> and as the looſing of the <hi>four</hi> Angels which were bound in that great River, <hi>chap.</hi> 9.14. ſignifyed the <hi>Turks</hi> breaking in and over-running the Nations,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179884:37"/>as a Plague (<hi>following Antichriſt</hi>) upon the Chriſtian WORLD: So the drying up of the Water of this <hi>ſame</hi> great River, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.12. ſignifyeth the waſting and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominion, Power, and People, as a Plague upon them for ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the way of the LORD and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and aiding, aſſiſting, and helping his and his peoples Enemies, whom God hath purpoſed to deſtroy utterly; <hi>That the way of the Kings of the EAST might be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> verſ. 12.</p>
                  <p>By the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Jews,</hi> who are called Kings, becauſe of the Kingly Dignity which God will put upon them in that day, <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.8. <hi>The Kingdom ſhall come to the Daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.1, 2, 3. <hi>Thou ſhalt be a Crown of Glory in the Hand of the Lord, and a Rayal Diadem in the Hand of thy God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> becauſe they ſhall come from the <hi>East Countries,</hi> at leaſt ſome of them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.5. <hi>I will bring thy Seed from the Eaſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The way that is to be <hi>prepared</hi> for the <hi>Jews,</hi> is two-fold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> For their Converſion.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> For their return unto their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179884:37"/>own <hi>Land,</hi> by taking the <hi>stumbling-block</hi> out of their <hi>way,</hi> Iſa. 57.14.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are a very great Stumbling-block unto the Converſion of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> are a great impediment unto their return unto their own Land, unto which God hath promiſed to bring them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21, 22, 25. and to that end God will have both theſe ſtumbling-blocks re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way of his Antient People the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which followeth in the 13, 14, 15, 16 verſes of this Chapter, is not any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per effect of this Vial, nor any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but rather an <hi>interval</hi> of time betwixt the <hi>ſixth and ſeventh</hi> Vials, wherein ſome remarkable things are to be tranſacted in order to the pouring forth of the <hi>ſeventh</hi> Vial, and therefore contain a praeparatory Viſion thereunto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In which Viſion</hi> John <hi>ſaw three Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors or Agents ſent from the Dragon, the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, to the Kings of the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Dragon</hi> is that old <hi>Serpent</hi> called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> which is the <hi>Devil,</hi> chap. 20.2. The <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>civil</hi> State or <hi>political</hi> Powers, <hi>which Beast roſe out of the Sea,</hi> chap. 13.1. The <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> is the Eccleſiaſtical State,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179884:38"/>
                     <hi>which is the Beaſt that roſe out of the Earth,</hi> chap. 13.11. He is here called the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> becauſe now he is unmasked, and his Vizard pluck't off, <hi>to wit,</hi> his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed likeneſs unto the Lamb, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.11. And now he is diſcovered to be that Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and falſe Prophet which was to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The three unclean Spirits like Frogs,</hi> verſ. 13. are their Embaſſadors or Agents, called <hi>Spirits,</hi> for their ſubtilty and activity, and pretending to be ſpiritual men, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>principally</hi> about Religious and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Affairs, (<hi>like</hi> Ahabs <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> 1 King. 22.21, 22. <hi>who deceived the Kings of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah, <hi>in perſwading them to go up to</hi> Ramoth Gilead <hi>to Battel</hi>) and therefore are ſaid to be Spirits of <hi>Devils,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles:</hi> as the Devil raiſed up falſe Chriſt's, and falſe Apoſtles; ſo he doth falſe Prophets, <hi>purpoſely</hi> to deceive the Kings of the Earth, and the Inhabitants of the Earth, that they may not receive the true Chriſt, believe the true Apoſtles, nor regard the Teſtimony of the true Prophets of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Before <hi>John</hi> ſets down the <hi>ſucceſs</hi> of this their <hi>Negotiation,</hi> he writes a word of warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>as it were a Parentheſis,</hi> verſ. 15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behold I come as a Thief,</hi> &amp;c. that is to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179884:38"/>ſay, <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and <hi>unexpectedly,</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.43, 44. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed is he that watcheth</hi> for my coming, <hi>and keepeth his Garments</hi> white and clean, and faſt girded unto him; <hi>leſt he walk na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and they ſee his ſhame,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27.</p>
                  <p>The ſuccſs of their Negotiation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>And he gathered them together into a place, called in the Hebrew Tongue,</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageddon. He gathered them together, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> the Dragon, <hi>which is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> by his Frogs, <hi>thoſe unclean ſpirits,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <hi>them</hi> together, <hi>viz. the Kings of the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Armageddon</hi> we are to underſtand the name of a place, which the Jews ſhall give after they have gotten ſome conſiderable victory over the <hi>Turks,</hi> and therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it <hi>Armageddon, the place of deſtruction of an Army;</hi> which <hi>happily</hi> may have an <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lluſion</hi> unto that great <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aanites</hi> at the Waters of <hi>Megiddo,</hi> Judg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.19. when <hi>Siſera</hi> the chief Captain of <hi>Jabin,</hi> with all his Hoſts, fell by the hand of <hi>Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Barack,</hi> where was made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch a <hi>total</hi> deſtruction, that it is ſaid, <hi>Judg.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.16. <hi>And the Host of</hi> Siſera <hi>fell upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dge of the Sword, and there was not a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eft.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:179884:39"/>
                  <p>And ſuch an <hi>univerſal</hi> deſtruction will be the effect of this Battel at <hi>Armageddon,</hi> chap. 19.20, 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the ſeventh Angel poured out his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al into the Air,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Object</hi> of this <hi>Vial</hi> is the <hi>Air,</hi> which notes the <hi>univerſality</hi> of the <hi>Subjects</hi> upon whom the <hi>wrath of God</hi> is poured out of this ſeventh <hi>Vial.</hi> The <hi>Air</hi> fills all places, no <hi>Subject</hi> can be more general then the <hi>Air.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the <hi>Air,</hi> here we are to underſtand all Nations, Kingdoms, and People; all Places, Perſons, and Things, that oppoſe the Kingdom, Worſhip, and Government of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his <hi>Sion,</hi> Iſa. 60.12.</p>
                  <p>The Earth, Sea, Rivers, Sun, and Seat of the Beaſt's Kingdom is deſtroyed by the former Vials; And by this ſeventh Vial ſhall be deſtroyed all things whatſoever remains of <hi>Sathans</hi> Kingdom; Who is called, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>The Prince of the power of the Air.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other ſix <hi>Vials</hi> were poured out upon their particular <hi>Objects,</hi> but this ſevent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Vial is poured out into its Subject; which notes the ſpreading and dilating of it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into every part of <hi>Satan's</hi> and the Beaſt'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdom, for the utter deſtruction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179884:39"/>every thing therein that remained.</p>
                  <p>So then the wrath of God poured out of this Vial, will diffuſe and ſpread over,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>The whole Kingdom of Antichriſt, or the Beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>The remaining Dominion and Kingdom of the Turks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thirdly, <hi>The whole Kingdom of the Dragon, that old Serpent, which is the Devil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And when all theſe <hi>Enemies</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by the pouring out of this ſeventh <hi>Vial,</hi> then comes a great Voice out of the Temple of Heaven, (<hi>to wit, the Viſible Church of God on Earth, reſtored unto her primitive Purity, and made glorious,</hi> Iſa. 60.7, 12, 13, 14.) ſaying, It is DONE, <hi>chap.</hi> 10.6, 7. viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Myſtery of God is finiſhed, as he hath declared to his Servants the Prophets.</hi> This Voice is Chriſt<hi>'s, chap.</hi> 21.5, 6. <hi>He that ſat upon the Throne, ſaid unto me, It is DONE.</hi> This Voice is ſaid to come from the <hi>Throne</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of Heaven, in this 17. verſe; <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> It came from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſat upon the <hi>Throne,</hi> chap. 21.5, 6. and implies now Chriſts Kingdom ſhall be ſet up, and <hi>he</hi> himſelf ſhall <hi>ſit</hi> upon the <hi>Throne,</hi> chap. 3.21. and all his Saints with him.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:179884:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there were Voices, and Thundrings, and Lightnings; and there was a great Earth-quake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p>The like to this was the effect of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> riſing, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.13. upon which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions the tenth part of the City fell; ſo here by this great Earth-quake, <hi>the great City is divided into three parts,</hi> verſ. 19. Fractions, or Diviſions, note the utter ruine of the Roman-Antichriſtian-Politick-and-Eccleſiaſtick-State, Power, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Kingdom of the Beaſt; <hi>For a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Cities of the Nations fell,</hi> verſe 19. <hi>litterally,</hi> ſuch Nations as come to help the Beaſt, and the <hi>Turk</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>People. Mystically</hi> by the Cities of the Nations, we may underſtand <hi>National Churches.</hi> The great Whore is called the great City; ſo the Harlots, <hi>who are her Daughters,</hi> chap. 17.5. are here called the Cities of the Nations. If the Catholick Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be the great City, then the National <hi>Romiſh</hi> Churches, may alſo be called the Cities of the Nations; which ſhall fall in the Day of the Lords contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with all Nations, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.22. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.30, 31, 32, 33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And great Babylon came in remembrance before God,</hi> verſ. 19.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179884:40"/>
                  <p>By great <hi>Babylon</hi> here is <hi>primarily</hi> meant, <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the royal City of the great <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Secondarily,</hi> All his Principalities, Domininions, and Kingdom, propheſied of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.4, 5, 24, 25, 32.</p>
                  <p>Neither am I alone in this my Opinion, for Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> and others are of the ſame Jugement. And my Reaſons are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe the great <hi>City,</hi> and great <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> are <hi>contradiſtinguiſhed</hi> one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this 19 <hi>verſe,</hi> and therefore cannot the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe great <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid here to come in <hi>remembrance</hi> before the LORD, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not literally be applied to the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> for that was the Seat of the Beaſt, upon which the fift <hi>Vial</hi> was poured out; nor can it be <hi>mystically</hi> applyed unto the whole Kingdom of the Beaſt, for that had come in remembrance before the Lord, in pouring out the former five <hi>Vials.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Turk hath been, is, and will be as great an Enemy againſt the Jews (<hi>eſpecially in their return to their own Land</hi>) as the Pope hath been, is, and will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gentile Saints; And whereas both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> together with the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> being now at laſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179884:41"/>all combined together, with all their <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> againſt the LORD and his <hi>Saints,</hi> both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they ſhall all drink of the Wine of the fierceneſs of Gods wrath, which ſhall be poured out of this ſeventh <hi>Vial</hi> without mixture of Mercy; <hi>chap.</hi> 19.19, 20, 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Every Iſland fled away, and the Mountains were not found,</hi> verſ. 20.</p>
                  <p>By Iſlands and Mountains, here we may underſtand,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Places of hiding, and of ſecurity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.19, 21. and <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.6, 7, 22. But there will be no ſecurity not hiding, for every Iſland fled away, and the Mountains were not found, ſo that their <hi>ruine</hi> will be <hi>inevitable</hi> without any refuge or ſhelter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By Iſlands we may underſtand ſuch things as are ſeparated from a common, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome ſacred uſe, as Iſlands are ſeparated from the main Land by Waters that go round about them. Such are all Popiſh <hi>Conſecrated</hi> and <hi>Dedicated</hi> things, <hi>viz.</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, Deanaries, Cathedrals, Churches, Chapples, Priories, Nunneries, Church-Lands, and Revenues; all theſe, and all of theſe kinds ſhall be ſequeſtred and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from their Sacred, or rather Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179884:41"/>and Idolatrous uſes, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto a common and civil uſe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſuch Conſecration, Dedication, Aſſignation, or Separation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By Mountains, we may underſtand, the great Powers and Dominions of the Earth, the Monarchs and Monarchies of this WORLD, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.25. <hi>Theſe ſhall not be found;</hi> for they ſhall be broken and deſtroyed utterly, and they ſhall be made like the Chaff of the Summer Threſhing-Floors, which the Wind carrieth away; <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. <hi>And no place was found for them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there fell upon men a great Hail out of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 21.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Hail</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> ſignifies ſome more immediate Judgements and Plagues of God. Here may be ſome <hi>Alluſion</hi> to the deſtruction of the Canaanites by great Hailſtones from Heaven, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.11. Or elſe this is that great Storm of Gods <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> Judgements threatned <hi>Prophetically</hi> againſt <hi>Gog</hi> in the Land of <hi>Magog, Ezek.</hi> 38.2, 18, 19, 21, 22, 23. <hi>And I will plead againſt him with an overflowing rain, and great Hailſtones, fire and brimſtone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And men blaſphemed God,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 21.</p>
                  <p>This is the Effect of Gods moſt juſt and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179884:42"/>righteous Judgements upon all his unpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Enemies, <hi>they Blaſphemed God.</hi> This was the Effect of the Plagues poured out of the Fift <hi>Vial,</hi> Verſe 9, 11. which was the Beaſts former practice, Chap. 13.6. The Beaſt was a Blaſphemer from the Beginning, and ſo continues unto his End; He lives and dies in his Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt God, <hi>and periſheth for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as touching the <hi>Time,</hi> when theſe <hi>Seven Vials</hi> ſhall be poured out, though I have a very honorable eſteem of thoſe Godly and Learned Expoſitors of this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> who are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that three or four of theſe Seven Vials are poured out already; Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that they have ſaid, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I am not of their mind, out do rather think, <hi>That none of thoſe ſeven Vials are yet poured out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Scripture-Grounds that I have to offer for my Opinion in this Point are theſe, <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. Becauſe, <hi>the Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony in Heaven is not opened,</hi> out of which Temple the ſeven Angels come forth with their ſeven golden Vials, Chap. 15.5, 6, 7. Which Temple I have proved before, to be <hi>the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179884:42"/>Heavenly State of the Church of God on Earth, reſtored in ſome Meaſure unto its Apoſtolical Conſtitutions, and primitive Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> which, when ſo, was called the <hi>the Temple of the Living God,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16.</p>
                  <p>Let Chriſtians conſider, that <hi>none</hi> of the Seven <hi>Vials</hi> are to be poured out until the Temple be opened, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> until the Church of God on Earth be reſtored in ſome meaſure unto its Apoſtolical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and primitive Purity, which is not yet done, and therefore <hi>no Vial is yet poured out.</hi> 2. Becauſe, <hi>Chriſt's Sackcloch Witneſſes and Warriers muſt be ſlain, and raiſed, and the Seventh Trumpet ſounded, before the Temple be opened, or any of the Seven Vials be poured out,</hi> Chap. 11.7, 11, 14, 15, 19.</p>
                  <p>But theſe things are not yet done, and therefore none of the Seven Vials are yet poured out. Let Chriſtians conſider, Are the Witneſſes ſlain, before their Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be finiſhed? Verſe 7. ſaith, <hi>When they ſhall have finiſhed their Teſtimony, the Beaſt, that aſcendeth out of the Bottomleſs Pit, ſhall make war againſt them, and ſhall overcome them, and kill them:</hi> And if theſe Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Warriers be ſlain, Are they Riſen and aſcended up to Heaven? (that is, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179884:43"/>an Heavenly State and Dignity) and have their Enemies been enlightned to behold them? as is propheſied they ſhall, Verſe 11, 12. Again, Hath the Seventh Angel ſounded his Seventh Trumpet? as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied Verſe 15. which Angel muſt Sound his Seventh Trumpet before this Wrath come, Verſe 18. I offer theſe three Reaſons to the ſerious Conſideration of Chriſtians, why the Seventh Angel hath not Sounded his Seventh Trumpet, <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. <hi>The Myſtery of God is not finiſhed,</hi> which muſt be done when the Seventh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel begins to Sound his Trumpet, Chap. 10.6, 7. 2. <hi>The Second Wo is not Paſt</hi> until the Witneſſes and Warriers be raiſed and aſcended, which muſt be done before the Seventh Angel Sound his Trumpet, Chap. 11.11, 12, 14, 15. 3. Upon the Sounding of the Seventh Trumpet, The Kingdoms of this World do become the Kingdom of Chriſt and of his Anointed, Chap. 11.15. But this is not accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which argues that the Seventh Angel hath not Sounded his Seventh Trumpet, which Seventh Trumpet muſt uſher in the <hi>Seven Vials,</hi> as the <hi>Seventh Seal</hi> did the Seven Trumpets, Chap. 8.1, 2, 6. whereby it is manifeſt that the Temple is not open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179884:43"/>nor any of the Seven Vials poured out.</p>
                  <p>And Thirdly, Becauſe, <hi>Thoſe Seven Vials contain the Seven laſt Plagues</hi> (Chap. 15.1. <hi>for in them is filled up the Wrath of God</hi>) which are Contemporary with the Victory, which the Saints ſhall get over the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and over his <hi>Image,</hi> and over his <hi>Mark,</hi> and over the <hi>Number</hi> of his <hi>Name,</hi> Chap. 15.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Standing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sea of Glaſs mingled with Fire,</hi> and ſinging that Triumphant Song of the Lamb, Verſes 3, 4. Which Victory the Saints have not yet Gotten, neither can they ſing that Triumphant Song, and therefore none of the Seven <hi>Vials</hi> are yet poured out. Let Chriſtians conſider, 1. That the Seven laſt Plagues will utterly Ruin and Deſtroy Antichriſt, Root and Branch, and that ſuddenly, Chap. 18.2, 8, 10, 17, 19. 2. That the Seven laſt Plagues contain that laſt Judgement of the great Whore (called <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi>) which doth precede the Marriage of the Lamb, Chap. 17.1. and 19.1, 2, 3, 7. 3. That the Seven laſt Plagues are the effects of the laſt War of the Beaſt and Falſe Prophet, and the Kings of the Earth againſt the Lamb, <hi>our LORD Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his Armies in Heaven, <hi>namely,</hi> his Saints <hi>who are Called, and Choſen, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179884:44"/>Faithfull,</hi> Who having Overcome and got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Victory over theſe Enemies of God, of Chriſt, and of his People, They pour out thoſe Vials of the laſt Plagues of God Almighty upon them, chap. 17.13, 14. chap. 16.14. chap. 19.19, 20. and chap. 18.6, 7, 8. All which Argues that the Seven Vials of Gods laſt Plagues are not yet poured out. 4. Becauſe <hi>the Firſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel hath not yet poured forth his Vial;</hi> And If the <hi>Firſt Angel</hi> hath not poured forth his <hi>Vial,</hi> then the <hi>Second, Third,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Seven Angels</hi> have not poured forth any of their <hi>Vials.</hi> But that the <hi>Firſt</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel hath not poured out his <hi>Vial</hi> [beſides what hath been ſaid for the proof of my Opinion, the Reaſons and Scripture-Grounds given for the ſame in general] I do humbly offer theſe following Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove. <hi>Viz.</hi> Though I Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thoſe Godly and Learned Men, and Bleſs the Lord for their worthy Labours in the Expoſitions of the Book of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Yet I cannot, <hi>(for the Reaſons before gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven)</hi> conſent with them who affirm that <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Wickliff, Huſſe, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. are meant by the Firſt <hi>Angel,</hi> that poured out the firſt <hi>Vial:</hi> nor can I be of their Opinion, who ſay by this <hi>Angel</hi> is meant, the Sweden
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179884:44"/>Wars, nor the Long Parliament; nor any other Perſons or Plagues, which have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen the Antichriſtian Roman Political and Eccleſiaſtical State unto this Time: Becauſe I ſee not the Effects of this Firſt <hi>Vial</hi> accompliſhed upon the Earthly, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and Worldly Intereſt of the grand Apoſtates of theſe Laſt Times. Which thing cauſeth me to continue in my <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> both in general touching all the Seven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and in <hi>particular</hi> touching the Firſt <hi>Vial,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I ſhall be convinced by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Light, and ſound Reaſon grounded thereon; Viz. <hi>That the Firſt Angel hath not poured out his Vial.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Argument</hi> for the proof thereof is from chap. 18.21. <hi>Thus with violence ſhall that great City</hi> Babylon <hi>be thrown down, and ſhall be found no more at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have already declared, that the Vials of the Laſt Plagues do contain that laſt Judgement of the great Whore <hi>(called Myſtery Babylon)</hi> mentioned Chap. 18. And all Expoſitors of this Propheſie of the <hi>Revelation</hi> do affirm the ſame: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, This Compariſon chap. 18.21. holds eſpecially in theſe two things; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt;</hi> as a great <hi>Milſtone</hi> caſt into the Sea doth not ſometimes ſink, and another
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179884:45"/>while ſwim; now falling down, and then riſing again; Thus, <hi>or ſo</hi> When any of the Seven <hi>Angels</hi> pour out any of their <hi>Vials</hi> upon any part of the Roman Antichriſtian State of the Beaſt's Political and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Kingdom, that <hi>Part</hi> upon which the <hi>Vial</hi> is poured forth ſhall fall, periſh, and riſe no more; <hi>no nor be found no more at all,</hi> chap. 18.11, 14, 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As a great <hi>Milſtone</hi> caſt into the <hi>Sea</hi> falls and ſinks down irrecoverably unto the <hi>Bottom;</hi> Thus, <hi>or ſo</hi> when the Firſt Angel hath poured out his <hi>Vial</hi> upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> upon the <hi>Sea,</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> upon the <hi>Rivers,</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the <hi>Fift</hi> upon the <hi>Seat</hi> of the Beaſts Kingdom, <hi>Babylon (like a Milſtone)</hi> ſinks to the Bottom; <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> The ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction of the Great Whore <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery Babylon</hi> is ſuddenly effected by the pouring out of the Vials of the Laſt Plagues of the fierceneſs of the Wrath of God upon her, chap. 18.8, 10, 17, 19. <hi>for in one Hour ſhe is made deſolate.</hi> But we ſee not ſuch Effects of any Plagues of God yet upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Seven Laſt Plagues or <hi>Vials</hi> are not any of them poured forth, no not the <hi>Firſt</hi> of them.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:179884:45"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Argument,</hi> that proves the <hi>Firſt</hi> Vial is not <hi>yet</hi> poured out is, <hi>Becauſe</hi> That noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and grievous Sore <hi>(which is the Effect of the Firſt Vial)</hi> is not yet fallen upon the <hi>Men,</hi> which had the <hi>Mark</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and upon them that did worſhip his <hi>Image,</hi> chap. 16.2. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That noiſom Sore will cauſe both all the Lovers and Friends of <hi>Babylon</hi> for ever to ſtand aloof, yea, after off from her, and from them that the Sore is on, <hi>to wit,</hi> Popes, Cardinals, Biſhops, Prieſts, Jeſuits, Fryars, Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And upon them that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped his Image; namely, all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Crucifix-adorers, Image-worſhipers, Croſs-creepers, Altar-bowers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chap. 18.10, 15, 17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That grievous Sore will cauſe ſuch exquiſite Torment, and pain unto the Men that had the Mark of the Beaſt, and upon them which worſhipped his Image, That the Smoke of their Torment aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up for ever and ever, chap. 14.9, 10, 11. and when the Kings of the Earth, the Merchants of the Earth, and the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, Saylers, and all the Company of Ships, and as many as Trade by Sea, ſhall ſee the Smoke of her Burning, and the Torment of her Worſhippers, they will
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179884:46"/>ſtand afar off and Cry, Alas, alas! for in One Hour ſhe is made Deſolate, chap. 18.18, 19.</p>
                  <p>But there is no ſuch notſom and grievous Sore fallen upon the Men, that had the Mark of the Beaſt, nor upon them that Worſhipped his Image. The Popes, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Prelates, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor the Papiſts, who worſhip Images, Crucifixes, Croſſes, Altars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have not been ſo tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by any plagues of God, that the Smoke of their Torment hath Arcended for ever and ever; Nor have the Kings of the Earth, the Merchants of the Earth, nor they that Trade by Sea ſo ſeen the ſmoke of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Burning, as to ſtand afar off for fear of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Torment, Concluding and Confeſſing that in one hour ſhe is made Deſolate; Read ch. 18.9, 10, 15, 17, 18, 19. And therefore I again conclude, (being the more confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Opinion, by theſe Arguments) <hi>That the Firſt Angel hath not yet poured out his Vial:</hi> And if the Firſt <hi>Vial</hi> be not <hi>yet</hi> poured out, then <hi>none</hi> of the Seven <hi>Vials</hi> of the <hi>Laſt Plagues</hi> are <hi>as yet</hi> poured out.</p>
                  <p>And until theſe Seven <hi>Vials</hi> of the Laſt Plagues of God be all poured our, The Kingdom of the Antichriſt will not be <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> Deſtroyed; nor will all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179884:46"/>the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this WORLD become the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the LORD, and of his Saints: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>gh there will be ſome conſiderable <hi>Beginnings</hi> of the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Eſtabliſhing</hi> of the Kingdom of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt before the laſt <hi>Vial</hi> be poured out.</p>
                  <p>Touching which Two <hi>Kingdoms, viz.</hi> of Antichriſt, and of Chriſt, I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to offer in the <hi>Third Part</hi> of this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which I judge meet for the Saints in this GENERATION to know: Into the right underſtanding whereof, the LORD guide my heart and yours by his Holy Spirit and Word to his Glory, that we may know what we ought to do in this DAY of our GENERATION. Amen, and Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:47"/>
                  <p>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES.</p>
                  <p>The Third Part. Touching the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and the KINGDOME of CHRIST.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rev. 11.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The Kingdoms of this WORLD are become the KINGDOM of our LORD and of his CHRIST, and HE ſhall REIGN for ever and ever.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:48"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179884:48"/>
                  <head>Apocalyptical MYSTERIES. The Third Part. Touching the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and the KINGDOME of CHRIST.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev. 11.15.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The Kingdoms of this WORLD are become the KINGDOM of our LORD and of his CHRIST, and he ſhall REIGN for ever and ever.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe <hi>Seventh</hi> Angel mentioned in this verſe is the <hi>Angel</hi> of the third WOE, denounced againſt the Inhabiters of he EARTH, chap. 8.13.9, 12. and 11.14. which third WOE containeth all thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179884:49"/>righteous Judgments of God that are to be executed upon <hi>Myſtical</hi> BABYLON by pouring out of the <hi>Seven</hi> VIALS of the <hi>Laſt</hi> PLAGUES of <hi>Almighty</hi> God upon the KINGDOM of the BEAST, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this WORLD be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the KINGDOM of CHRIST and and of his SAINTS <hi>for ever and ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the Kingdoms of this WORLD, we may underſtand, 1. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally,</hi> All the Kingdoms of the World, that are upon the face of the Earth: 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.26. <hi>to wit,</hi> All Rule, Dominion, Power, and Government in all Nations, and Kingdoms of the WORLD. 2. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally,</hi> All the Kingdoms of the DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NION of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYLON, <hi>Jer</hi> 34.1. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37, 38. alſo of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia, Ezra</hi> 1.2. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.39. likewiſe of <hi>Alexande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> the Great, King of <hi>Grecia, Dan.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10, 21, 22. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.3. and 2.39. and laſtly of the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> the Kings of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which is the <hi>fourth</hi> Kingdom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Monarchy</hi> of this WORLD, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.40, 41, 42. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.23, 24, 25. 3. <hi>Specially.</hi> All the Nations, Languages, Kingdoms, and People that are under the DOMINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, Rule, Power, Government and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179884:49"/>Kingdom of ANTICHRIST, the Man of SIN, and Son of PERDITION, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>to wit,</hi> the BEAST of the EIGHT Head, with two HORNS, Who aſcended out of the Bottomleſs PIT, and ſhall go into PERDITION, chap. 17.8, 11. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with All the <hi>Dominions,</hi> Rule, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Power, and Government of all the <hi>ten</hi> Kings, who received their <hi>Power</hi> one hour <hi>(that is, at the ſame Time)</hi> with the BEAST, and have given their Power and Strength unto the BEAST, chap. 17.12, 13. <hi>Theſe are the Kingdoms of this WORLD; which ſhall become the KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM of our LORD, and of his CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which doth Concern the <hi>Saints</hi> in this GENERATION to know, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdoms of this WORLD, is, 1. <hi>How they became the Kingdoms of AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICHRIST; and</hi> 2. <hi>How they ſhall become the Kingdom of CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To that End, let the Saints Conſider,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Kingdoms of this WORLD, <hi>to wit,</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrio—Chaldean</hi> Monarchy, the <hi>Medio—Perſian</hi> Monarchy, the <hi>Grecian</hi>— Monarchy, and the <hi>Roman</hi>—Monarchy had their <hi>Dominions</hi> and Kingdoms given them by the God of Heaven, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37, 38, 39, 40. <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.2. Who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179884:50"/>have by the Succeſſion of <hi>Divine</hi> Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had and exerciſed their Dominion, Power, and Authority over all Nations, People, and Languages under their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment; <hi>Under whoſe Yoke and Dominion God for the ſins of his people</hi> Iſrael <hi>put them alſo and their Kings, Deut.</hi> 28.15, 25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.6, 7, 8, 11, 12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37, 38, 39, 40. <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1-7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Fourth</hi> Kingdom or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, which is the <hi>Roman</hi>-Monarchy, or <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Caeſars</hi> in the dayes of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, was God's ORDINANCE of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and thoſe <hi>higher</hi> POWERS unto which all the <hi>Saints,</hi> and every <hi>Soul</hi> who lived under the <hi>Roman</hi> Government, ought to be <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> for Conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would not have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted <hi>Titus</hi> to put the <hi>Saints</hi> in mind to obey <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> (as he did, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.) if there had been no <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> then in <hi>Being:</hi> or if they had been <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and not God's <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> writing to the <hi>Saints (ſcattered through Pontus, Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Capadocia, Aſia, and Bythinia)</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179884:50"/>them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>To ſubmit themſelves unto every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c. verſe 15. <hi>for ſo is the will of God,</hi> &amp;c. if the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> Kings, and Governours then in <hi>Being,</hi> were not <hi>Lawfull Powers,</hi> had no <hi>lawfull Authority,</hi> nor were the ORDINANCE of God, as well as <hi>they were</hi> the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Man?</p>
                  <p>Let it be alſo well and ſeriouſly Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>firſt,</hi> That Chriſt and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples called the <hi>then</hi> Roman Powers, <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Luke</hi> 12.11, 58. and <hi>Acts</hi> 16.19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Apoſtle exhorted the <hi>Saints</hi> to pray for <hi>Kings (in their Church-Aſſemblies)</hi> and for all that then were in <hi>Authority,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did ſubmit <hi>themſelves</hi> unto the <hi>Roman</hi>-Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſats, Kings, and Governours then in Power, paid them <hi>Tribute</hi> or Cuſtom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.24, 25, 26. and commanded the <hi>Saints</hi> ſo to do, <hi>and to continue in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Rom.</hi> 13.5, 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi>-Power, and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical-Government of the Caeſars, Kings, and Governours of the fourth Monarchy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179884:51"/>or <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this WORLD; became <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> when the Beaſt received his Power, his Seat and great Authority from the Dragon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. that old Serpent, <hi>which is the Devil,</hi> chap. 20.2. and exerciſed that Power, both <hi>Tyrannically</hi> over the Eſtates and Perſons of Men, and <hi>Coercively</hi> over the Conſciences of Men and Women, Cauſing all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and bond to ſubject themſelves unto the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> and to receive his <hi>Mark, Name,</hi> and <hi>Number,</hi> and to Worſhip the Beaſt, or elſe they muſt neither buy nor ſell, but be Killed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>This POWER of Antichriſt, <hi>which the Devil gave him,</hi> was ſignified unto <hi>John</hi> by a BEAST with <hi>two</hi> HORNS like a Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Horns</hi> do ſignifie <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> in the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of Scripture, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.4. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.20, 24, 25. and <hi>two Horns,</hi> imply a <hi>twofold</hi> Power and Authority, <hi>to wit,</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical and Eccleſiaſtical; theſe two Horns are <hi>ſaid to be</hi> like the Lamb, <hi>becauſe</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> pretends to have both his <hi>Political,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> POWER and great <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> from Chriſt, and to exerciſe both
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179884:51"/>for Chriſt; whereas indeed <hi>HE</hi> had his Throne, his Power and great Authority from the <hi>Dragon, the Devil and Sathan,</hi> chap. 23.2. and doth exerciſe it againſt Chriſt and his Saints, chap. 11.7. and 13.15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Politick</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick POWER</hi> is the ſame <hi>POWER,</hi> that the <hi>ten</hi> Kings of the <hi>Roman</hi>-Kingdom received alſo <hi>ONE HOUR</hi> with the <hi>Beaſt, that is to ſay,</hi> at the ſame Time, when the <hi>Beaſt</hi> received his Antichriſtian <hi>POWER</hi> from the <hi>DRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GON,</hi> chap. 17.12. Which mixt Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Eccleſiaſtical Power the <hi>ten</hi> Kings <hi>or Kingdoms</hi> do exerciſe for the <hi>BEAST</hi> againſt <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his Saints, chap. 17.13, 14. and chap. 19.19, 20, 21. <hi>unto their own Deſtruction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now aſſoon as this <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſt</hi> with his <hi>ten</hi> Horns was <hi>riſen</hi> out of the <hi>SEA, to wit,</hi> the troubles, tumults, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, and diviſions of the <hi>Roman</hi>-Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, when by the <hi>WARS</hi> of the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi>-Empire was diſſipated into <hi>ten</hi> Kingdoms; At which <hi>Time</hi> alſo this ſame <hi>Beaſt</hi> with his two Horns, is ſaid to <hi>Riſe</hi> out of the <hi>EARTH, that is to ſay,</hi> out of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of an <hi>earthly-minded CLERGY;</hi> who departed from the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179884:52"/>
                     <hi>FAITH,</hi> as was afore Propheſied, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. ſhould come to paſs in the <hi>latter</hi> Dayes. <hi>I ſay, from that Time,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>-Monarchy, and Political Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fourth Kingdom ceaſed (though not to be a Kingdom, and to have a Power, a Throne, and great Authority, yet) to be a <hi>lawfull POWER,</hi> and an <hi>OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINANCE</hi> of God: And therefore ought not to be obeyed, nor ſubmitted unto by any of the Saints of God, neither in any <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Commands; for that is to <hi>WORSHIP</hi> the <hi>BEAST,</hi> or his <hi>IMAGE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the Saints conſider, 1. That thoſe, who ſhall Reign with Chriſt, have not <hi>WORSHIPPED</hi> the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> chap. 20.4.2. As it was dangerous to <hi>WORSHIP</hi> the <hi>Beast</hi> a little after his Riſe, chap. 8.7, 13. ſo it will be damnable to <hi>WORSHIP</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> a little before his fall, chap. 14.8-12.3. Thoſe that ſhall ſtand with the Lamb upon <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> with his Fathers <hi>Name</hi> in their Fore-heads, and learn to Sing that <hi>New SONG</hi> before the <hi>Throne,</hi> chap. 14.1, 3. are ſuch <hi>Saints</hi> as have gotten the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory</hi> over the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and over his <hi>Image,</hi> &amp;c. chap. 15.2, 3.</p>
                  <p>So then I conclude from what hath been
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179884:52"/>ſaid, upon Scripture-Grounds, touching the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>This WORLD</hi> becoming the Kingdom of <hi>ANTICHRIST,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the Saints in this GENERATION ought not to Obey, nor to ſubmit themſelves unto the</hi> Roman-<hi>Antichriſtian-Politick and Eccleſiaſtick-POWER, Rule, Authority, Dominion, and Government of the BEAST, nor of the ten Kings or Kingdoms, who have given their POWER and Strength unto the Beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond thing which I judge neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Saints in this <hi>GENERATION</hi> to know, is, How the Kingdoms of this <hi>WORLD</hi> ſhall become the <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God ſhewed unto his <hi>Prophet Daniel</hi> in his <hi>VISIONS</hi> of the <hi>Night,</hi> how the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> of the <hi>WORLD</hi> ſhould become the <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, Dan.</hi> 2.34.35, 44, 45. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14, 18, 22, 26, 27. <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Kingdoms of the <hi>WORLD</hi> ſhall be broken in pieces by a <hi>STONE</hi> cut out of the <hi>MOUNTAIN</hi> without hands, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34, 35, Which <hi>STONE</hi> is Chriſt, <hi>Plal.</hi> 118.22. <hi>Matth:</hi> 21.42. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 6. and alſo the Churches of Saints, <hi>his Jeruſalem,</hi> called a <hi>Burthenſom Stone, Zech.</hi> 12.3.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179884:53"/>
                  <p>The Kingdoms of this <hi>WORLD</hi> ſhall be broken in pieces; <hi>firſt,</hi> by falling upon the <hi>Stone, viz.</hi> Chriſt and his People, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.17, 18. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall fall upon that STONE ſhall be broken,</hi> Zech. 12.3. <hi>In that DAY I will make</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a burthenſom STONE; All that burthen themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces. Secondly,</hi> The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this <hi>WORLD</hi> ſhall be broken in pieces by the <hi>STONE, to wit,</hi> Chriſt and his Peoples falling upon them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.44. <hi>But on whomſoever this STONE ſhall fall, it will grinde them to Powder:</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> 51, 19, 20-24. <hi>Thou art my Battle-AXE, and Weapons of WAR; for with thee will I break in pieces the Nations, and with thee will I destroy Kingdoms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>STONE</hi> ſmiting the <hi>Fourth Kingdom</hi> upon his <hi>FEET</hi> of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> and breaking them in <hi>Pieces,</hi> was expounded unto the Prophet, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.17, 18. <hi>But the Saints of the Most High ſhall take the KINGDOM, and poſſeſs the Kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 7.24, 25, 26. <hi>But the Judgement ſhall ſit, and they ſhall take away his Dominion, to conſume and to destroy it unto the End:</hi> read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Kingdoms of this <hi>WORLD,</hi> being broken in pieces by the <hi>STONE</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179884:53"/>upon them, The <hi>STONE</hi> will become a great <hi>MOUNTAIN,</hi> and fill the Whole <hi>EARTH, Dan.</hi> 2.35. <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> Chriſt and his Saints ſhall have the <hi>DOMINION</hi> in all the <hi>EARTH, Dan.</hi> 7.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>And I beheld till the BEAST was ſlain, and his BODY deſtroyed, &amp;c. As concerning the</hi> REST <hi>of the Beaſts, they had their</hi> DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINION <hi>taken away,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold</hi> ONE <hi>like the</hi> SON <hi>of Man,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And there was given him</hi> DOMINION <hi>and Glory, and a</hi> KINGDOM, <hi>that all People, Nations, and Languages ſhould ſerve him,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26, 27. <hi>But the Judgement ſhall ſit, and they ſhall take away his</hi> DOMINION, &amp;c. <hi>And the</hi> KINGDOM <hi>and Dominion, and the greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven, ſhall be given to the People of the Saints of the Moſt High,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As the WAY for the KINGDOM of Chriſt and his Saints to be ſet up, is made by the Breaking in pieces the Kingdoms of this WORLD, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. <hi>For the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Kingdom that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh, yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted:</hi> So the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt and his Saints ſhall be <hi>inlarged</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhed:</hi> 1. By the <hi>Converſion</hi> of Sinners, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> unto Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.3, 5, 8,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179884:54"/>10, 11, 14, 15. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25, 26, 27. 2. By the Pouring out the SPIRIT upon all Fleſh, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3, 4, 5. 3. By the UNION of all the Saints, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. and <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.9. <hi>The</hi> LORD <hi>ſhall be</hi> KING <hi>over all the</hi> EARTH, <hi>in that</hi> DAY <hi>there ſhall be</hi> ONE <hi>Lord, and his Nome</hi> ONE. And 4. By the RESTITUTION of all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. <hi>I will Reſtore thy Judges as at the first,</hi> Iſa. 60.17. and Iſa. 49.6. <hi>It is a light thing that thou ſhouldest be my Servant to raiſe up the Tribes of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and to</hi> RESTORE <hi>the preſerved of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then the Whole CRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ATION ſhall be <hi>delivered</hi> from the BON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAGE of Corruption, and <hi>Restored</hi> into the Glorious LIBERTY of the Children of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, 21, 23.</p>
                  <p>That which the Saints of God in this GENERATION are to know, touching the KINGDOM of Chriſt, are theſe things following, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the KINGDOM of our LORD Jeſus is not of this WORLD, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36. Nor is it of a <hi>Worldly</hi> Conſtitution; but it is a ſpiritual and <hi>heavenly</hi> Kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18. and will be a <hi>glorious</hi> State, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1, 2, 15, 19, 21, 22. of a NEW
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179884:54"/>
                     <hi>Heaven,</hi> and of a NEW <hi>Earth,</hi> wherein dwells <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. which is the <hi>State</hi> of the Holy <hi>City,</hi> the NEW <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that cometh down from God out of <hi>Heaven, Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2. Then ſhall they call <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the THRONE of the LORD, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.13, 17. which NEW <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> God will make a PRAISE in the EARTH, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.2, 3, 7. An <hi>eternal</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and the joy of many <hi>Generations, Iſa.</hi> 60.14, 15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This KINGDOM of Chriſt is the THRONE of his <hi>Father David, Iſa.</hi> 9.7. and <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32, 33. which <hi>Throne Solomon</hi> his <hi>Son (who was a Type of Christ)</hi> ſat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he <hi>reigned</hi> over all the Kingdoms that God gave to him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.21. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe THRONE our LORD Jeſus Chriſt ſhall ſit, and <hi>Reign</hi> over all the Kingdoms of the WORLD, <hi>Who is the onely</hi> POTENTATE, <hi>the</hi> KING <hi>of Kings, and</hi> LORD <hi>of Lords,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.14. who ſhall be KING of all the EARTH, <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.14. with whom the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall <hi>Reign</hi> on EARTH, and ſhall Rule and Govern the <hi>Nations, (not by the Laws of Men, but)</hi> by the Laws of God; <hi>Which are true Laws, right Judgements, and good Statutes,</hi> Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah 10.13, 14. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> our LOKD,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179884:55"/>and <hi>Judah</hi> his People is our <hi>Law-Giver,</hi> Iſa. 33.22. and Pſal. 101.8. <hi>The Kingdom ſhall come to the Daughter of Jeruſalem, and the first</hi> DOMINION <hi>to the Daughter of Sion.</hi> Mich. 4.7, 8. <hi>And out of Sion ſhall go forth the Law,</hi> Mich. 4.1, 2, 3-7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This KINGDOM of our LORD will <hi>begin</hi> before the Kingdoms of this WORLD <hi>End,</hi> Dan. 2.44. <hi>In the Dayes of theſe Kings</hi> (to wit, the ten Kings of the Fourth Monarchy and Kingdom of the Beaſt) <hi>ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a</hi> KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM; which is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. Then will our LORD Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt take unto him his great POWER and <hi>Reign, Rev.</hi> 11.15, 17, 18. At which the Nations will be angry, and the Heathen will <hi>Rage,</hi> The Kings of the EARTH will ſet themſelves, and the <hi>Rulers</hi> of this WORLD will take <hi>Counſel</hi> together againſt the LORD, and againſt his <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Yet God will ſet his KING upon his <hi>Holy</hi> HILL of <hi>Sion,</hi> and will give him the <hi>Heathen</hi> for his <hi>Inheritance,</hi> and the uttermoſt parts of the EARTH for his <hi>Poſſeſſion. Pſal.</hi> 2.1-8. <hi>And the LORD ſhall</hi> REIGN <hi>over them in MOUNT-Sion, from henceforth even for ever,</hi> Mich. 4.7, 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Though the KINGDOM of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179884:55"/>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall <hi>begin</hi> before the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this WORLD <hi>End;</hi> And though all the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this WORLD ſhall become the KINGDOM of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt; Yet the great Glory and Perfection of Chriſts <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall be in the WORLD to COME. Then ſhall ALL things be put in SUBJECTION under the Feet of <hi>Chriſt, Hebr.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>Which <hi>World</hi> to COME is contradiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the WORLD <hi>that</hi> NOW IS, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. Called <hi>this</hi> WORLD, <hi>in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction</hi> from <hi>that</hi> WORLD, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.34, 35, 36. The Apoſtle alſo ſpeaketh of the DOMINION of <hi>this</hi> WORLD, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.21. and of the POWER of the WORLD to COME.</p>
                  <p>The WORLD to COME is not that <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> State of God's <hi>Kingdom</hi> of GLORY in <hi>Heaven;</hi> but it is the <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> State of the KINGDOM of Chriſt on EARTH, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. <hi>That ſame</hi> WORLD, <hi>even</hi> THAT, <hi>that is to</hi> COME; <hi>to wit,</hi> The inhabited WORLD to Come, wherein the PEOPLE of God ſhall build Houſes, and inhabit them, according to Gods Promiſe, <hi>in that day,</hi> when he will <hi>Create</hi> New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and a new Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 25. and <hi>Amos</hi> 19.11, 14. <hi>And ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179884:56"/>build up the Tabernacle of</hi> David, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Dominion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the KINGDOM of Chriſt on EARTH ſhall be given to the Saints, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. and be Managed by them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Laws of Chriſt; and to that End the Saints, (<hi>who ſhall Reign with Chriſt on Earth</hi>) ſhall be <hi>rarely</hi> Qualified, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Work, and <hi>Kingly</hi> Government: for, 1. They ſhall be all Righteous, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. They ſhall do no Iniquity, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.13. They ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fault before the THRONE of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. 2. The Saints ſhall be SPIRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED for Government, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.5, 6. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Government, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10. and ſtrengthned for Governing, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.5, 8. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24, 25. 3dly, and Laſtly, The Saints ſhall be <hi>cloathed</hi> with <hi>Humility,</hi> ſo that they ſhall Caſt down their <hi>Crowns</hi> at the Feet of Chriſt, their KING, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10, 11. Exalting HIM alone, ch. 5.9, 10. And they ſhal be <hi>Endued</hi> with Courage, <hi>Clad</hi> with Zeal, and <hi>Girded</hi> with Strength and Truth, that they may binde Kings in <hi>Chains,</hi> and Nobles in <hi>Fetters</hi> of IRON, and <hi>Execute</hi> upon them the JUDGMENT written, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>This</hi> HONOUR <hi>have all his SAINTS, Pſal.</hi> 149.1, 2, 6, 7, 8, 9. which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179884:56"/>was Propheſied of <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.19-24. <hi>Thou art my Battle-Axe and Weapon of WAR, for with thee will I break in pieces the Nations, and with thee will I deſtroy Kingdoms, and with thee will I break in pieces Captains and</hi> RULERS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo Zech. 12.5, 6. <hi>In that DAY will I make the GOVERNORS of</hi> Judah <hi>like a Hearth of Fire among the Wood, and like a Torch of Fire</hi> in a Sheaf, <hi>and they ſhall devour all the PEOPLE</hi> (the Enemies of Chriſt) <hi>round about.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The Goſpel of this <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of Chriſt ſhall be preached in all the <hi>WORLD</hi> for a <hi>WITNESS</hi> to all <hi>NATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, Mat.</hi> 24.14. And therefore the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of Chriſt <hi>cannot</hi> be ſet up in any <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion until</hi> the <hi>GOSPEL</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> be <hi>firſt</hi> preached in that <hi>Nation;</hi> And then that <hi>NATION,</hi> Kingdom, or <hi>PEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLE,</hi> which do believe the <hi>GOSPEL</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> preached unto them, and are made <hi>WILLING (in the DAY of God's POWER, Pſal.</hi> 110.3.) to Admit the Saints to <hi>RULE</hi> and <hi>GOVERN</hi> that <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> according to the <hi>LAWS</hi> of our <hi>LORD</hi> and <hi>KING Jeſus,</hi> ſhall become the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt: But that <hi>Nation, Kingdom</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> which will not receive the <hi>TESTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONY</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179884:57"/>the <hi>WITNESS</hi> of the Goſpel, and Kill the <hi>WITNESSES</hi> of Chriſt, ſhall be utterly Waſted, and Deſtroyed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. And our <hi>LORD</hi> Jeſus Chriſt will put down all RULE, all <hi>AUTHORITY,</hi> and all <hi>POWER,</hi> that are his <hi>Enemies,</hi> and wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not Submit unto his <hi>DOMINION,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 25. and <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seventhly, WHEN</hi> this <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>LORD</hi> is Eſtabliſhed on <hi>EARTH,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>POWER</hi> and great <hi>GLORY,</hi> and all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdoms of this <hi>WORLD</hi> are become the <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of Chriſt; The <hi>Thouſand</hi> Years of the Reign of Chriſt and his Saints being Expired and Ended, Then Will Chriſt come <hi>again,</hi> and all the Saints with <hi>HIM, Zeph.</hi> 14.5. and 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17, 18. then will be the <hi>General RESUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RECTION,</hi> and the <hi>Laſt JUDGMENT,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22, 23. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 12, 13, 14. Which being paſt, Chriſt ſhall deliver up the Kingdom unto God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>that GOD may be ALL in ALL,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 25, 28.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179884:57"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
